<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises, one of the latter day of iudgement: the other of the ioyes of Heauen</title>
            <author>I. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 581 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14058.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900352</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900352</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72410)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1992:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises, one of the latter day of iudgement: the other of the ioyes of Heauen</title>
                  <author>I. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 131, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Thomas Creed, and are to be solde at his house in the Olde Change, at the signe of the Eagle and Childe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Judgment Day --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO TREATISES, One of the Latter day of <hi>Iudgement:</hi> The other of the Ioyes of <hi>Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Cor. 15.52.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In a moment, in the twinckling of an eye, ſhall the Trumpet blow, and the dead ſhalbe raiſed, and we ſhalbe chaunged that are found aliue.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 24.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Except thoſe dayes ſhould bee ſhortened, no fleſh ſhould be ſaued: but for the elects ſake, thoſe dayes ſhalbe ſhortned.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Creed, and are to be ſolde at his houſe in the Olde Change, at the ſigne of the Eagle and Childe. 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150982:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150982:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire hath bene of a long time, to ſet downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, the <hi>Excellent,</hi> the <hi>Decaied,</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Eſtate of man;</hi> if by Gods grace, I might, or may as yet in good time performe it. Wherof I haue finiſhed a great part, the which if God giue good ſucceſſe, in due time, ſhall be added to that which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie publiſhed: wherein I haue ſet downe the <hi>Excellent Eſtate of man:</hi> by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring how God created him after his Image.</p>
            <p>The thing that I haue aimed at, both in that, and this, or any thing elſe, that hereafter I ſhall do, is only to profit and to do good. And therefore at this time, and according to this time, and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome &amp; dangerous dayes of this world; prognoſticating the vtter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay
<pb facs="tcp:150982:3"/>thereof, I haue thought good by this Treatiſe of the Latter Iudgement, to put you in remembrance, that you may be ready and prepared, when the Trumpet ſhall blowe, and when we ſhall be called to our account. That euery one of vs in the meane time, may haue this in our minde, and in our mouth; <hi>Good Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs to thy kingdom, and ſhorten the daies of ſinne. Ezekias</hi> deſired to haue his dayes prolonged. And vnto <hi>Ioſias,</hi> it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced for a bleſſing, that his time ſhould be ſhortned. Which of theſe two was the better choyce, that I leaue to thy reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: perſwading thee to that, which I take to be beſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Suprema cogita; Cor ſit in aethere:</l>
               <l>Foelix qui potuit mundum contemnere.</l>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine to his power, <hi>S. I.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:150982:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A TREATISE OF</hi> the latter day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 10.36. to 43.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Ye know the word which God hath ſent to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> preaching peace by Ieſus Chriſt, which is Lord of all. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the word which came through all <hi>Iudea,</hi> beginning in <hi>Galile,</hi> after the Baptiſme which <hi>Iohn</hi> preached. To wit, how God annointed Ieſus of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> with the holy Ghost, and with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: who went about doing good, and healing all that were oppreſſed of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: for God was with him. And wee are witneſſes of all things which hee did, both in the land of the Iewes, and in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:</hi> whom they ſlew, hanging him on a tree. Him God raiſed vp the third day, and cauſed that he was ſhewed open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; not to all the people, but vnto the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, choſen before of God, euen to vs,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150982:4"/>which did eate and drinke with him, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he aroſe from the dead.</p>
                  <p>And he commaunded vs to preach vnto the people, &amp; to teſtifie, that it is hee, that is ordained of God, a Iudge of quicke and dead.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very one no doubt is deſirous to know, what ſhall bee done at the latter day, at the day of doome and iudgement. A doctrine very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to them that haue any care of themſelues, and of their owne ſaluation; and very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo to prouoke vs to the loue, knowledge, and feare of God. And ſo much the more profitable and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it is, by how much the nearer that day is at hand, and approacheth, beeing as our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, hard at the doores.</p>
            <p>Concerning theſe words which I haue read vnto you, I ſhall require you to haue regard vnto theſe principall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150982:4"/>Firſt what is the cauſe why this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall iudgement ſhalbe.<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> Secondly, the declaration of this iudgement. Thirdly, who ſhall be the iudge. Laſtly, how it pertaineth to the wicked &amp; to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; wherunto I haue thought good to ad an exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the better to be prepared.</p>
            <p>The cauſe wherfore Chriſt ſhal come to iudgement, principally is no other, but that which procured death vnto vs, and the laſt &amp; generall iudgement, ſhall make that matter more certain; not only that this bodily death, which is a ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſoule &amp; body for a time, ſhal not ſerue the turne, &amp; be inough to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that puniſhment which we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: but alſo that ſome ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to eternal death, both of body and ſoule, as indeed we ſhould be all in that eſtate, were it not for the benefite of Chriſt his death. The ſinne &amp; tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Adam,</hi> as alſo the ſins and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of vs al, was &amp; is the cauſe, why God is diſpleaſed with vs, and why his wrath is vpon vs, and why we are ſubiect vnto death, and why wee ſhall appeare before the iudgement ſeate of God. <hi>Pſal: 90.9. For when thou art angry,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150982:5"/>ſaith the Prophet, <hi>All our dayes are gone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we bring our yeares to an end, as it were a tale that is told; wee conſume away in thy diſpleaſure. Thou wilt ſet our miſdeeds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and our ſecret ſinnes in the ſight of thy countenance.</hi> Our miſdeeds haue procured death, had not Chriſt died for vs, and roſe againe from death, to deliuer vs from feare. They were the cauſe, why we were ſhut out from heauen; had not Chriſt aſcended vp into heauen, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vs an entrance, they had brought vs to the fearefull iudgement of God, and to the heauy and wofull ſentence of euerlaſting condemnation and endleſſe deſtruction, if by the meanes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, we might not be deliuered from it. For when we were at hell gates, and appointed to deſtruction, he came with this ioyfull meſſage: <hi>Come againe ye children of men.</hi> As indeed his firſt comming here on earth, was to ſaue and not to deſtroy, and to call ſinners to repentance, that they might bee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the fauour of God, and haue their ſinnes forgiuen them; but this his ſecond comming, at the latter end of the world, ſhall be to iudge, to tender ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150982:5"/>and to deſtroy thoſe ſinners, who in this life were againſt his glory, and their owne ſaluation; to call them now to account, whom when time was he called to repentance, and who now ſhall be puniſhed by the extremitie of the wrath of God. Who if they had well regarded it in their life time, might haue bene receiued into fauour, their ſinnes being forgiuen: ſo that at the day of iudgement, they ſhould not haue beene put to any hazard for them, nor ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the daunger of loſſe of body and ſoule for them. Here in this life they might haue eſcaped that, which in that day they ſhall not be able to auoyd. We ſee in all well ordered Realmes, that if it were not for offences committed, and for the manifold outrages, of robbers, theeues and murderers, the Iudges nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not ride their circuit, neither ſhuld there be any iudgement heard of. But as before that man had diſobeied God, this ſentence was giuen out; <hi>If thou doeſt eate, thou ſhalt die the death:</hi> ſo ſeeing he hath diuerſly, and moſt notoriouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, therefore hath God appointed a day to ſit in iudgement, to make this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150982:6"/>ſentence more ſure and knowne, and to put it in ful execution. We read of <hi>Enoch</hi> that holy man, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 4.10.14. that hee walked with God, that is, that he pleaſed him, &amp; was beloued of him: ſo that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he liued among ſinners, God tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, and tooke him vp into heauen, leaſt wickedneſſe ſhould alter his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. For his ſoule pleaſed God, and therefore God haſted to take him away from wickedneſſe, leaſt he ſhould giue his conſent vnto ſinners, and fal into the ſelfſame condemnation with them. But becauſe wee haue grieuouſly offended his maieſty, therfore ſhal we be brought before his iudgement ſeat. <hi>For righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is immortall, but vnrighteouſnes brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth death.</hi> Thus then through the bane of ſin, wee are ſubiect vnto Gods wrath and heauy iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which in the end of the world, &amp; at the ſecond comming of Chriſt, ſhall bee pronounced againſt vs. According to that we read, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Reioyce ô yoong man in thy youth, &amp; let thy heart cheare thee in the dayes of thy youth, and walk in the waies of thy heart, &amp; in the ſight of thine eies. But know, that for al theſe things, God will bring thee to iudgement.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150982:6"/>But here many of vs follow the courſe of the ſtream, with all other <hi>Atheiſts</hi> &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly perſons, who becauſe they ſee, that God delayeth the time of his comming to iudgement, therfore they think there ſhalbe no iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at all. Of whom the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> doth thus prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in his 2. Epiſtle, Chap. 3.3.<note place="margin">Some mock at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, as though it ſhould not be.</note> 
               <hi>This firſt vnderſtand</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that there ſhal come in the laſt dayes mockers, which will walke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their luſts: And ſay, where is the promiſe of his comming? For ſince the fathers died, all things continue alike from the beginning of the creation.</hi> Seed time &amp; harueſt, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and winter, one generation decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and an other commeth in place thereof. And becauſe they ſee the ſame courſe of the world to continue, that was from the beginning, they are ready to ſay as thoſe of whom I made mention, when I opened vnto you the doctrine of reſurrection; Our life ſay they is but a breath, and ſo forth; and when we are dead, there ſhall be no more remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of vs: and therefore we will doo thus and thus, euen what we liſt. Which is a token of Gods iudgement vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150982:7"/>who ſometime ſuffereth the obſtinate offender, to do in a maner what hee liſt, as we read, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81. <hi>v.</hi> 11.12. <hi>So I gaue them vp to the hardneſſe of their heart, and they haue walked in their owne counſels.</hi> Where we muſt not imagine, that they can doo any thing againſt Gods will, who doth ſo bridle and reſtraine them, that they ſhall do no more, then that which hee will ſuffer them. God doth not onely reſtraine and bridle them, but further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, ſends his fearefull iudgements vp-them oftentimes, to ouertake them, that they may knowe there is a God that iudgeth the earth,<note place="margin">Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments in this world.</note> and that ſuch male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, are further reſerued vnto the day of iudgement. And therefore we ſee ſo many ſtrange and wonderfull exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods wrath daily before our eies. Which ſtrange examples, we cannot ſay are wrought by me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, becauſe they paſſe the compaſſe of mans reaſon, how they ſhuld be wrought, &amp; how they ſhuld come to paſſe: but that we may ſay as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> enchaunters ſaid, <hi>This is the finger of God:</hi> that is to ſay, this is the worke and puniſhment of God, when he bringeth vpon men and women, ſore
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150982:7"/>plagues, ſudden death, and ſtrange ends; ſo that we cannot otherwiſe chuſe, but confeſſe it to be ſo. Theſe puniſhments God doth ſend, not onely to feare vs from the like offences that they haue committed, vpon whom God hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed and executed his iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but alſo that wee may bee put in minde, that there is a iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come, and that hee hath begun the anger and wrath of his fierce iudgement here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. Which plagues and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are fore-tokens, and as it were manifeſt ſignes of the iudgement to come.<note place="margin">The feeling of this iudgement, engraffed in vs by nature.</note> Yea there is an inward feeling of this iudgement, engraffed in vs by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For they that commit any ſinne, as murder, fornication, adultery, blaſphemie, and many other the like; albeit they can ſo conceale the matter, that none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue do know it, or be priuy vnto it, yet oftentimes they haue a griping in their conſcience, and they feele as it were the very flaſhings of hell fire within them. Which is a ſtrong reaſon to ſhewe that there is a God, before whoſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate, they muſt anſwere for their ſinnes, offences and miſdeeds.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150982:8"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Some ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the knowledge of the latter iudgement.</note>Yet ſuch there are, who being poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an euill humor, and ouercome of their naughtie &amp; wicked deſires, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of Gods heauy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, cannot preuaile to moue them to rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, or to haue any remorſe of their euill life, but rather they endeuour to ſuppreſſe the feeling of that which by nature, and by the light of reaſon is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and are deſirous wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to forget it. As S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of them, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5. <hi>This</hi> ſaith he <hi>they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly know not, that the heauens and earth are reſerued vnto fire, againſt the day of iudgement, and of the deſtruction of vngodly men, they willingly know not.</hi> So when it comes into mens conſciences, that there is a iudgement to come, and when they feele an inward feare within them, for their miſdeeds, they doo not take profit by this inward feeling of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whereby it pleaſeth God to call them to the knowledge of themſelues, to be humbled in his ſight, to call for mercy &amp; forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, to turne to God in newneſſe of life, that ſo they might preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Gods iudgement &amp; be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But they are ſo mightily ouercome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150982:8"/>of ſinne, and of their euill deſires, which rule and raigne within them, that they turn this inward feeling, and this inward calling of God, to their owne hurt. And as the faſhion of the world is, they deſire to put away ſuch ſad thoughts, &amp; betake themſelues to merry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant conceits, or elſe to other paſtimes, of carding, dicing, bowling, &amp; ſuch like. So that the diuel through their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, holdeth him ſtill in his chaines, whereas they might ſeeke meanes to be deliuered from the ſubiection, whereby the diuell retaineth them in his ſeruice, and keepeth them within his power, if they themſelues were any thing willing to be deliuered and ſet free. <hi>By a ſad looke</hi> ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 7.4.5. <hi>the heart is made the better. And it is better to be in the houſe of mourning, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the houſe of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> When the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 24.26. in the preſence of <hi>Felix</hi> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, <hi>diſputed of righteouſneſſe, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and of the iudgement to come. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix trembled;</hi> &amp; therwithall did ſuppreſſe this matter, by betaking himſelfe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſineſſe. <hi>Go thy way ſaith he for this time, and when I haue conuenient time, I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150982:9"/>will call for thee.</hi> Hee vſed not this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward feeling of the knowledge of Gods iudgement to the beſt, that is to repent and to turne to God, but as a worldly minded man, hee would haue no ſuch dumps to daunt his minde, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from his vain pleaſures, althogh then and at that time, he were full deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toucht in conſcience.</p>
            <p>Well, although ſome do mock at the iudgement day, as though it ſhould not come, or elſe ſuppreſſe the knowledge thereof within themſelues, that they may follow their luſts, eate, and drinke, and riſe vp to play; that they may enioy the vanities and pleaſures of this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory world, ſo long as they liue in the world; yet they, and we together with them, may learne two profitable leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Firſt becauſe as wee thinke it is long before God doo come to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (although oftentimes he begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his iudgement here vpon earth, by ſtrange examples, which as I haue ſaid, are the forerunners of his laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) we may learne I ſay, that with God, a thouſand yeares, which we count a whole world, is but as yeſterday that is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150982:9"/>paſt; and therefore that it is not long, though it ſeeme ſo vnto vs. Secondly, that God hereby ſheweth his patience and long ſuffering, his great compaſſion and mercy, in that hee would not the death of a ſinner, but waiteth for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendment; and thinketh that in good time, we will hate and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde our wicked and ſhamefull life, and turne to him, that we may be ſaued; for hee would haue all men to come to repentance. And therefore the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Paul. Ro.</hi> 2.4. doth greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and ſpeake againſt them, who ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make little account, or deſpiſe the riches of Gods bountifulneſſe, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and long ſuffering, not knowing that the bountifulneſſe of God, leadeth to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance. But we after our hardnes, and hearts, which either cannot or will not repent, heape vnto our ſelues wrath againſt the day of wrath; and of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the iuſt iudgement of God. For indeede it is like to be with vs as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> they cared not for <hi>Noahs</hi> warning and preaching vnto them, and rather made a mocke of it, they followed their owne hearts deſire,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150982:10"/>and did whatſoeuer, ſeemed good in their owne eyes. So ſhall not we in this laſt Iron age of the world, regard any warning, nor reſpect the counſell of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wiſh vs good: neither thinke of iudgement, nor what ſhall befall vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatly doted vpon the pleaſure of ſin, which at the laſt ſhall vaniſh, and in time to come, ſhal haue a bitter reward. Wheras if we forethink with our ſelues, of theſe heauy matters, &amp; of the wrath of God, which ſhall be perceiued by his iudgement, which we muſt of force en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, if we repent not; I ſay, if we ſhould forethink theſe matters, we ſhould learn truly to fear God, &amp; to forgo our ſelues, that is, deny our naughty deſires &amp; ſins, and pleaſures, that ſo Gods wrath might be diminiſhed toward vs, and that hee might not enter into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with vs. As ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90.11. <hi>Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth the power of thy wrath? for euen as a man feareth, ſo is thy diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ought to be affected, ſeeing the ſin, and the flouriſhing eſtate of the wicked.</note>Here alſo the mindes of the faithfull and godly, are to be prepared to patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that although they ſee many vngodly minded men, to make a mocke of the iudgement to come, and ſo to continue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150982:10"/>in their ſinfull liues, and doo what they liſt, &amp; that they are not puniſhed in this world, by Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, plagues and puniſhments; yet let vs perſwade our ſelues, that they ſhal not eſcape, though God ſuffer long, and though we in our weake mindes think it too long. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thogh the wicked may ſay within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vauntingly and yet full vainely, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay.</hi> Chap. 28.15. reciteth their ſpeeches; <hi>We haue made a couenant</hi> ſay they, <hi>with death: and with hell, are we at agreement: though a ſcourge runne ouer and paſſe through, it ſhall not come at vs. Yet their couenant with death ſhalbe diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled: and their agreement with hell, ſhall not ſtand.</hi> And when a ſcourge runneth ouer and paſſeth through, are they not ſometime trode downe by it, and taken away, when they make litle or no reckoning of any ſuch matter? The holy Apoſtle doth giue the reaſon, of the certaintie of their puniſhment, if not in this world, yet in an other. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>For if god ſpared not the Angels that had ſinned, but caſt them downe into hell: Nay if Gods iudgement begin at his owne houſe, and if God doo puniſh his owne people;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150982:11"/>And if the righteous ſcarcely bee ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and ſinner appeare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17.18. Wherefore let vs not be as they were of whom the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> ſpeaketh, Chap. 3.15. <hi>Wee count the proud bleſſed; euen they that worke wickedneſſe are ſet vp, and they that tempt God, yea they are deliuered from all daungers. So that it is in vaine to ſerue God, and what profit is it that we haue kept his commandements, and that we walked hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly before the Lord of hoſts?</hi> Theſe are the ſpeeches, of many weake and diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and decaied mindes, becauſe they ſee the flouriſhing eſtate of the wicked. But as it is ſaid in the <hi>Reue. Chap.</hi> 22.11. <hi>They that be filthy, and will ſo continue without amendment, let them ſee what ſhall be the end, and let them be filthy ſtill; Hee that is vniust, let him be vniuſt ſtill.</hi> So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is ſaid on the contrary part, <hi>They that are iuſt and righteous, let them bee righteous ſtill; and they that are holy, let them be holy ſtill;</hi> let them not faint in the courſe that they haue taken in hand, but remember what is written in the ſelfeſame Chapter. The comming of the Lord to iudgement is at hand; <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150982:11"/>ſaith he, <hi>I come quickly,</hi> and let vs wiſh, <hi>Euen ſo come Lord Ieſus.</hi> And as for the reſt, let vs perſwade our ſelues thus, as we reade, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>The Lord knoweth how to deliuer the godly out of temptation; and to reſerue the vniuſt vnto the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be puniſhed.</hi> The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his beſt time, and when it is moſt expedient that we ſhould be deliuered: In the meane time, let vs not faint, and vtterly caſt away our hope, if God doo not preſently puniſh the wicked. For God doth ſo order his puniſhments and his iudgements, that although he ſuffer the wicked for a time (which indeede if we do rightly conſider, is but a moment of time) yet he will not leaue them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed at the laſt; as we vſe to ſay, It is neuer too late that comes once. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſeeing that God hath appointed a day of iudgement, they ſhall not eſcape, though his iudgement doo not preſently take hold on them. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſlip from God, or auoyd him, but are bound as it were with ſecret chaines, ſo that in time to come they ſhall bee drawne do iudgement; who are kept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that time to be puniſhed, euen as the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150982:12"/>oxe which is fed &amp; fatted to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. So that, it behoueth vs to wayt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the time of the laſt iudgement, which God hath appointed, and ſo to continue in hope and patience, vnto the ende of our liues: and not to be offended, thogh the wicked be not puniſhed. But euery one of vs, ought to haue reſpect to our owne wayes, to keepe our ſelues within the compaſſe of Gods feare, leaſt that fall vpon vs, which we thinke and looke ſhould fal vpon other, and wonder with our ſelues why it is not ſo.</p>
            <p>Againe, as the word of God dooth inſtruct vs, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall cauſes, why God delayeth this day of iudgement. One is, that the day of iudgement ſhall not come, vntill the number of the elect be fulfilled: as we may reade, <hi>Reu.</hi> 7.2. <hi>And I ſaw another Angel come vp from the Eaſt, which had the ſeale of the liuing God, and he cried with a loud voyce, to the foure Angels, to whom power was giuen, to hurt the earth and the ſea, ſaying: Hurt ye not the earth, neither the ſea, neither the trees, till we haue ſealed the ſeruants of our God in their foreheade.</hi> And then ſhall the iudgement be, as we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150982:12"/>reade, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.22. <hi>Except thoſe daies ſhould be ſhortned, there ſhould no fleſh be ſaued, but for the elects ſake thoſe dayes ſhalbe ſhortned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this Iudgement is delaied, that the ſtubborne and vngodly may be thereby without excuſe. For they haue warning inough, exhortations &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings at all times, what their ſinnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and what they are to looke for, ſo that they cannot be ignorant of the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t day, neither can they ſay, that they are oppreſſed at vnawares.</p>
            <p>And this may ſuffice to proue, not onely that ſinne and our offences is and ſhalbe the cauſe of iudgement: but alſo they that ſin of ſet purpoſe, &amp; in ſcoffing and mocking ſort, think that there ſhall be no iudgement, or rather do ſuppreſſe and bury within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, if it might be, the inward feeling &amp; knowledge of the ſame, &amp; that to their great hurt, ſhal not eſcape y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heauy ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance of God, thogh yet they be forborn. Alſo that the minds of the godly be not troubled, although they do not preſently ſee that god doth exerciſe his iudgments &amp; puniſhments vpon them: and that they faint not in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150982:13"/>wel doing, but ſtill hold on their courſe, remembring that God hath appointed a day of iudgement, vpon the which they muſt ſtay and depend, and vnto the which they muſt referre all matters, and then ſhall all their cauſes be heard, and all their griefes eaſed.</p>
            <p>Notorious ſinnes, procure notorious puniſhments in this world: but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at the iudgement day, ſhall the full meaſure of all plagues and puniſhments be fulfilled. And ſo much the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in this world, many rule and raigne in their wickedneſſe, and are as it were ſcotfree: and as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>They come in no miſfortune like other men, neither are they plagued according to their deſerts.</hi> But the latter day, the day of doome and iudgement, is and ſhall bee their day of aſſiſes, and of their perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all execution. Wherefore let none of vs all ſuppreſſe and baniſh the inward fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and knowledge of this iudgement day, ſeeing that by nature, it is engraffed into our hearts and ſecret knowledge: but rather let in haue that effect in vs, that of right it ought to haue. We ſee it true in worldly matters, and I would
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150982:13"/>to God, it were as true in heauenly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. For queſtionleſſe, the forethought of the aſſiſes, and of the execution, doth feare many from their wicked purpoſes, and makes them take an other courſe. And ſo no doubt, would the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the iudgement day preuaile with vs, but that wee are careleſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that it is farre hence, and that we ſhall neuer ſee it: nay more then that, many thinke it ſhall neuer be. Well, how far off the iudgement day is, God knowes, and wee may euery day looke for: but by the way, take this for thy learning, that thy dying day, is and ſhall be thy iudgement day: and aſſure thy ſelfe, that thou ſhalt ſo find it. For when thy ſoule is parted from thy body, then ſhalt thou preſently appeare before Gods iudgement ſeate, to giue thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and pray that it may be to thy comfort, and not to thy deſtruction. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Now for the deſcription and declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this generall iudgement, which is the ſecond principal matter in this text, that both they which either mocke or doubt of the iudgement to come, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150982:14"/>they alſo which are well neare perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereof, might be throughly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, and certainly enformed: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the order and maner of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſet downe, in the ſcriptures and word of God, principally and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the 25. Chap. of <hi>Mat. verſ.</hi> 31. and ſo forth, in theſe words. <hi>And when the Sonne of man commeth in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him, then ſhall hee ſit vpon the throne of his glory. And before him ſhall be gathered all Nations; and hee ſhall ſeparate them one from an other, as a ſhepheard ſeparateth the ſheepe from the goates. And he ſhall ſet the ſheep on his right hand, and the goates on the left. Then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand; Come ye bleſſed of my father, inherite the kingdome prepared for you, from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the world. Vnto them on the left hand he ſhall ſay: Depart fro me ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, into euerlaſting fire, which is prepared for the diuel and his Angels. And theſe ſhall go into euerlaſting paine, and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous into life eternall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which deſcription and declaration, cannot be more plainely, euidently, and briefly ſet downe, ſetting forth vnto vs;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150982:14"/>Firſt the comming of the Iudge, with his company, that is, al the holy Angels: Secondly, the general appearance of all the people of the world: Thirdly, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Iudge, in ſeparating the good from the bad. And laſtly, the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by definitiue ſentence without all reuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Al which matters, God willing ſhall be handled, when I come to entreate of the Iudge; ſo that I need not to ſtand vpon this point, but to referre you thither, where in a more fit place it may be conſidered.</p>
            <p>And as here the order of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is expreſſed, ſo in other places of ſcripture, other matters are ſpecified, which are very neceſſary, to giue vs fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnderſtanding herein. As firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the day when this iudgement ſhall be; the ſignes that ſhall go before this day; as alſo how ſuddenly it ſhall come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the day the Prophets do foretell, how terrible it is likely to be.<note place="margin">The day.</note> The day of the Lord ſay they, is a day of blacknes &amp; darknes; the earth ſhal tremble before him; the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſhall ſhake; the Sun &amp; the Moone ſhalbe dark, and the ſtars ſhal withdraw their ſhining.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150982:15"/>
            <p>This day is great and very terrible, and who can abide it? it commeth cruelly with wrath as fierce anger, and hee ſhall deſtroy the ſinners out of the earth. And becauſe the world ſhould haue ſome time to forethink themſelues, our Sauiour Chriſt hath giuen ſome war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, by the ſignes that ſhall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this iudgement day. As that there ſhall be falſe reachers abroad in the world, who ſhal deceiue, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the very elect and choſe children of God, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.24. Warres and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: Nation ſhall riſe againſt Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Kingdome againſt Kingdome: the father in matters of religion ſhalbe againſt the ſonne, and the ſonne againſt the father: the mother againſt the daughter: one friend againſt an other: great earthquakes in diuers places: hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, peſtilence: bitter perſecution of them that ſhall profeſſe Chriſt and his Goſpell: Charitie ſhall waxe cold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: men ſhall leade a leaud and ſinfull life, altogether careleſſe of the Iudgement to come: The Goſpell ſhall be publiſhed, and fewe ſhal regard it: it ſhall bee preached through the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150982:15"/>whole world, for a witneſſe vnto all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to make them without all excuſe, and then ſhall the end come. Feareful things ſhall be ſeene: the ſea and the waters ſhall roare, and mens hearts ſhall faile them for feare, and for looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe things which ſhal come on the world. The Sunne ſhall be darkened, and the Moone ſhall not giue her light: the ſtarres ſhal fall from heauen, and the powers of heauen ſhal be ſhaken, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the horrible trembling of the world is meant, together with the alteration and ouerturning of the whole courſe of nature. And after all theſe things, then ſhall appeare the ſigne of the Sunne of man in heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the ſignes of the latter day, ſhal worke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mindes of men.</note> The conſideration of which ſignes, ſhall worke diuerſly both in the godly and in the wicked. For the hearts of the wicked ſhall be hardned &amp; made worſe by theſe ſignes, as King Pharaohs hart, by Gods ſtrange puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, was more and more hardned, vntill the time of his deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that he was vtterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in the red ſea. Theſe ſignes, as they ſhal moue the godly minded, partly to repentance, in conſideration of theyr
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150982:16"/>ſinnes, and partly to comfort, in reſpect of ioyes to come: ſo the wicked contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, ſhall be giuen to diſpaire, and to curſe the houre that euer they were borne. And this is a ſecret iudgement vpon them, that they ſhall be blinded euen vntill the very houre of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, ſo that when they would ſeek for remedy, there ſhalbe none.</p>
            <p>The godly they wiſh for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Lord: <hi>Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly:</hi> for they know that his comming ſhall end their miſeries, and begin their ioyes, as Chriſt himſelfe doth comfort them. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.28. <hi>And when theſe things begin to come to paſſe, then looke vp, and lift vp your heads: for your redemption</hi> (that is the full accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the ſame) <hi>draweth neare.</hi> For then, as ſaith the Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Shall wee bee caught in the cloudes, to meete the Lord in the aire: and ſo ſhall we be euer with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt circumſtance of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is,<note place="margin">Sudden.</note> that it ſhall come vpon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and that moſt fearefully to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>For when they ſhall ſay peace, peace, and all in ſafetie, then ſhal come
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150982:16"/>vpon them ſudden deſtruction, as the trauel vpon a woman with child: and they ſhall not eſcape.</hi> As it fell out to the rich man in the Goſpell. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.20. <hi>Soule</hi> ſaith he, <hi>take thy eaſe, eat and drinke &amp; take thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, for thou haſt much good laid vp for many yeares.</hi> But he heard doleful words: <hi>O foole this night will they fetch away thy ſoule from thee.</hi> Or as when <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezer,</hi> vaunted himſelfe of his ſtately buildings, a fearefull voyce came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly vnto him: <hi>O King Nabuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer, to thee be it ſpoken, thy kingdome is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thee:</hi> Or as when his ſonne King <hi>Belſhaſar, Dan.</hi> 5.6. <hi>feaſting and hanquetting among his Concubines, ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there appeared a hand writing vpon a wall,</hi> declaring the end of his Kingdome and his death. This ſudden deſtruction ſhall worthily fall vpon them, who haue made a mock of this iudgement: who then ſhall feele the dint of Gods reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſword: and they that imboldned themſelues in all wicked waies, and euill naughtie practiſes, ſhall then know how far they went a ſtray. The wicked whom no lawe could refraine from their licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious life, and who haue died to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150982:17"/>ſight of men in peace; after they haue long enioyed their luſts and diuers plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, after much violence and wrong which they haue offered; after many miſdeeds which mans lawes ſhould haue corrected and yet let paſſe; although they haue eſcaped the iudgement of man, yet then ſhall they receiue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their deedes. But to the good and well diſpoſed, it is a watch-word, when they heare that the Iudgement day ſhall be vpon a ſudden. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with the fiue wiſe virgins, haue oyle in our Lampes, remembring Chriſt his forewarning, <hi>That which I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all men, watch.</hi> And ſo much briefly for the ſecond part of the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Text, namely of the deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and declaration of the latter Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Who ſhall be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudge.</note> The third generall matter which I propoſed vnto you, was concerning the Iudge, and who it ſhould be. And as it was ſaid of the Iudgement, that it ſhould be ſudden; ſo alſo ſhall the comming of the Iudge be. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.27. <hi>For as the lightning commeth out of the Eaſt, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150982:17"/>ſhineth into the Weſt, ſo ſhall alſo the comming of the ſonne of man be.</hi> He that was equall with God, and tooke vpon him the ſhape of a ſeruant, hee that was abaſed, deſpiſed, and perſecuted of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men: hee ſhall come in power and great glory to iudge the world, and to be reuenged of his enemies. He whom God hath placed at his right hand, farre aboue all principallitie, power, might, domination, and euery name that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not in this world onely, but alſo in that that is to come: hee it is that is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God, a Iudge of quicke and dead. Whoſe comming ſhall not be as at the firſt, poorely, and baſely, but with great maieſtie, and after a moſt glorious, wonderfull, and moſt dreadfull maner. He ſhall deſcend from heauen, not to come downe on the earth, but to ſit on the cloudes, as his tribunall ſeate and throne of Iudgement, hee ſhall come with a ſhout, and a maruellous great noiſe, with the voyce of the Archangel, and with the ſound of the laſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. <hi>For the Trumpet ſhall blowe, and the dead ſhall be raiſed</hi> (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.) <hi>and hee ſhall ſhewe himſelfe with thouſands of his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150982:18"/>mighty Angels, and that in flaming fire, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring vengeance vnto them that doo not know God, &amp; which obey not vnto the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Which ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power. When he ſhall come to be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his Saints, and to bee made mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous in all them that beleeue.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>Which glorious appearance of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, this heauenly Iudge that ſhall come in the latter end of the world, ſhall be of the more maieſtie, if we ſhall compare it to the deliuerie of the lawe, which then was both fearefull and terrible; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee reade, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. <hi>And the third day, when it was morning, there was thunders and lightnings, and a thicke cloude vpon the mount, and the ſounde of the trumpet louder and louder, euen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding loude, ſo that all the people that was in the campe was affraied. Then Moſes brought the people out of the tents, to meete with God, and they ſtood in the nether part of the mount. And mount</hi> Sinay <hi>was all on a ſmoke, becauſe the Lord came downe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150982:18"/>it in fire, and the ſmoake thereof aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as the ſmoake of a furnace, and all the mount trembled exceedingly.</hi> This appearing of the deliuery of the lawe, was to denounce a ſharpe puniſhment and curſe for ſinne: but this ſecond appearing at the ende of the world, ſhall bee with greater maieſtie and more terrible, by reaſon of the ful exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this curſe and puniſhment. And as <hi>Moſes</hi> was admitted into Gods preſence, but the people trembled and would not come neare: ſo ſhall this ſecond appearing, bee ioyfull to the godly, who ſhall meete with the Lord in the cloudes; but as for the reſt they ſhall mourne; and as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>who ſhall be able to abide it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then was but the mount on fire, but now ſhall the whole world bee on a flame: then onely the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> were called and aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: now ſhall all people, nations, and languages be gathered: then was there a curſe onely denounced, if they, and wee by them alſo beeing vnderſtood, ſhould tranſgreſſe and breake Gods law
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150982:19"/>and commaundements, but no preſent puniſhment followed: now ſhall there be no delay, but they ſhall in the ſame moment of time, receiue the ſentence of condemnation, and ſhall forthwith bee throwne into hell fire, to be tormented for euer. Therefore ſhall this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring be of greater glory, of greater ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and more terrible.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sonne of man,</hi> as yee haue heard, he ſhal be the Iudge of the whole world at the latter day: indeede no earthly man, but he that tooke vpon him the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man. Who alſo elſewhere, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſonne of God, and is the ſecond perſon in the reuerent and moſt holy trinitie: whom God hath not onely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to this office, but alſo hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Apoſtles, to preach and to publiſh it throughout the whole world, that it might bee as ſurely grafted into the mindes of men, as it is certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed by the determinate purpoſe of God. As we read, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.22. <hi>For the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudgeth no man, but hath committed all iudgement vnto the ſonne.</hi> Whereof the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo giueth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.32. <hi>God</hi> ſaith he, <hi>admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150982:19"/>all men euerywhere to repent: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath appointed a day, in the which he will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe, by that man whom he hath appointed, whereof he hath giuen an aſſurance vnto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi> By the force of which certaine perſwaſion, he chargeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to bee earneſt and carefull in his dutie, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>I charge thee therefore before God and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who ſhall iudge the quick and dead at his appearing preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</hi> Alſo the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2. Ep. 4.5. doth teſtifie the ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame thing, when as he exhorted thoſe whom he writ vnto, to deſiſt and leaue off their vngodly life, &amp; to depart from the company of the wicked, and not to be daunted in mind, thogh they ſhould be ſcoffed and mocked at their hands for ſo doing Encouraging them with a moſt forceable reaſon, that might throughly perſwade them: which is, that the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall be iudged: which iudgement they ſhall eſcape, that go from them, and turn to God in time, forſaking the waies
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150982:20"/>and counſels of the wicked. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the place of ſcripture is notable, and worthy of great regard, I think good to ſet it downe. <hi>It is ſufficient for vs</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>that we haue ſpent the time paſt of the life, after the luſt of the Gentiles, walking in wantonneſſe, lusts, drunkenneſſe, in glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and in abhominable idolatries. Wherein it ſeemeth to them ſtrange, that yee runne not with them vnto the ſame exceſſe of ryot,</hi> and continue in ſo doing, <hi>therefore ſpeak they euill of you; which ſhall giue accounts, to him that is ready to iudge quick &amp; dead;</hi> who is no other, but Ieſus Chriſt the Iuſt; as is manifect by thoſe places of Scripture, which I haue before alleaged.</p>
            <p>Which proofes being ſo ſubſtanciall, that Chriſt ſhall be the Iudge, and the matter ſo manifeſt, as I think there is no man but doth ſo beleeue, it ſhall ſuffice onely to haue touched it. And ſo let vs go forward, that wee may vnderſtand how Chriſt ſhall performe his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which eſpecially is laide downe in theſe three poynts. Firſt, that all the Nations and people of the world that euer haue bene, ſhall be gathered into his preſence, and the reaſon why they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150982:20"/>ſhall appeare is,<note place="margin">All people ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</note> that they ſhall be called to their account: Secondly, after triall of their cauſe, how he ſhall ſeperate the one from the other, the iuſt from the vniuſt, and the godly from the wicked. Thirdly, the execution of this Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in pronouncing of ſentence. All na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; people ſhalbe gathered into his preſence: <hi>For he ſhal ſend forth his Angels, with a great ſound of trumpet, and they ſhall gather together his elect fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foure winds, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one end of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the other; Math.</hi> 24.31. In the Parrable of the ſeede, it is ſet downe, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.30. that when harueſt comes, the reapers ſhall gather the tares, and binde them in ſheaues to burne them, and ſo foorth. Which Parable Chriſt enterpreting to his Diſciples, ſaith that the harueſt is the end of the world, and the reapers be the Angels, whom the ſonne of man ſhall ſend forth, and they ſhall gather out of his kingdome all things that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and them which doo iniquitie. Whereby may be perceiued, that both the good and the bad ſhalbe gathered into the preſence of the Iudge, becauſe the Text hath theſe words in the ſame
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150982:21"/>place. <hi>Then ſhall the iuſt men ſhine as the Sunne. For we muſt all appeare</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>before the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Chriſt; that euery man may receiue the things which are done in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or euill.</hi> Whereof S. <hi>Iohn</hi> had a manifeſt demonſtration, as we reade in his Reuelation, Chap. 20.11.12. <hi>And I ſaw</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a great white throne, and one that ſate on it, from whoſe face fled away both the earth and the heauen, and there place was no more found. And I ſawe the dead both great and ſmal ſtand before God;</hi> who ſhall iudge both the quicke and the dead, euen all that euer haue beene, are and ſhal be to the end of the world; as well thoſe that are dead and rotten in the earth, as thoſe which ſhall be found aliue at his comming, who ſhalbe chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in a moment, which change ſhalbe in ſtead of death.</p>
            <p>In iudgements that are practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, there are diuers conueiances vſed, not to appeare in iudgement: and for fauour, feare, bribes, and ſuch like matters, malefactors are bayled out of priſon, and bonds forfeyted, and they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150982:21"/>kept from the barre, and from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Iudge, and quitte by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation. But here the miniſters of this heauenly iudgement, to wit, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, ſhall not be blinded by any earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiderations. There ſhall be no entreaty no way to auoyd, no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but that they ſhall and muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. It is a ſtraunge matter, and not to be ſeene, that any Emperour, King, Prince, or any ſuch mightie Potentate, ſhould be called to iudgement, or ſhuld bee ſubiect vnto the ſentence of the Iudge. For why? as they ſay the Prince is aboue his law, and not to be cenſured by any. Subiects are vnder the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of lawes, and iudgement may paſſe vpon them: but as for the Prince and the higheſt in a Realme, who dare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll him if he do ill? But from this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this mighty &amp; heauenly Iudge, whom no power can reſiſt, ſhall neither Emperour, King, Prince, nor mighty Potentate be exempted, neither can they be diſpenced withall, but that of force and neceſſitie, they muſt make their perſonnall appearance. There ſhalbe no reſpect of perſons, high and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150982:22"/>and lowe, rich and poore: all ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Yea then it ſhalbe far better with the pooreſt begger, that hath liued in the feare of God, then with the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt Emperour, that in his life time hath had little or no regard to ſerue God. For true it is, that the mighty ſhall be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily puniſhed.</p>
            <p>All prophane perſons, leaud liuers, Atheiſts, perſecutors, which haue beene enemies to God, to his word, and to his miniſters, who haue wiſhed in their hearts, there were no God, nor any iudgement, who haue made a ſcoffe and contempt of all goodneſſe, and of the profeſſours and Miniſters thereof, they ſhall of force bee brought to this Iudgement. But what? To ſpeake in theyr owne behalfe? No, they ſhall not bee able. For at that time and there, they ſhall confeſſe theyr faultes and haynous offences, and make bitter lamentation, but all too late, and there ſhall they waight in trembling ſort, to heare their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And who is it amongſt vs,<note place="margin">No excuſes ſhall ſerue.</note> that knowes himſelf guiltie, that will declare
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150982:22"/>the truth, being called before a Iudge? but rather our mindes runne vpon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices and excuſes; how wee may blinde the Iudge, and defend our ſelues, and auoyd that which is toward vs. And ſo long as wee haue to deale with mortall men, it may ſo fall out, that our excuſes may ſerue the turne, and ſet vs cleare.</p>
            <p>But when our cauſe commeth to be tried before GOD, from whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is or can be hidde, and vnto whom nothing can bee ſecrete: then no excuſes can preuaile, neither ſhall any deuices helpe vs or blinde the Iudge. Our firſt parents, when God called them to their tryall, for tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his commaundement, and when the fled from God and his themſelues, (although they were ſtill in Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but fooliſhly they thought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) how did they aunſwere for themſelues, but by excuſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> hee ſpeakes for himſelfe, <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.12. and ſaith, <hi>The Woman which thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt to be with me, ſhe gaue me of the tree, and I did eate.</hi> The woman likewiſe ſhe thinkes to eſcape by that meanes;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150982:23"/>
               <hi>Eue,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eate.</hi> When King <hi>Saul</hi> had diſobei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gods commaundement, running <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the pray,</hi> being called to an account, he deuiſeth a currant excuſe, and ſaith, <hi>Yea, I haue obeyed the voyce of the Lord, and haue gone the way which the Lord ſent me, and haue brought</hi> Agag <hi>the King of</hi> Amelek, <hi>and haue destroyed the Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites. But the people tooke of the ſpoyle, ſheep and oxen, &amp; the chiefeſt of the things, which ſhould haue bene destroyed, to offer vnto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe, may <hi>Pilat</hi> be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who againſt his owne conſcience, condemned Chriſt to death, and yet would excuſe himſelfe, as though he were innocent in the cauſe <hi>Math.</hi> 27.24. <hi>When</hi> Pilat <hi>ſawe that hee auailed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that more tumult was made, hee tooke water and waſhed his hands, ſhaying? I am innocent of the blood of this iust mum</hi> In the deſcription of the latter iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Math,</hi> 25.44. wee read that ſome began to excuſe themſelues, ſaying: <hi>Lord when ſawe we thee an hungred, or a thirſt, or a ſtraunger, or naked, or ſick, or in priſon, and did not miniſter vnto thee.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150982:23"/>all this ſerued not, but vnto them it was ſaid: <hi>Depart from me ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into euer lasting fire.</hi> And ſuch part is <hi>Pilat</hi> like to receiue, for all his excuſe. King <hi>Saul</hi> his excuſe was not taken, our firſt parents eſcaped not for all their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, but dyed the death: and ſhall wee thinke our caſe to be better then theirse howſoeuer wee thinke, we ſhall not ſo finde it. There ſhall we appeare, when as no friend, nor and body ſhal be ſuffered to ſpeake for vs, and in our defence, and when a faire gloſing tale ſhall not bee heard, for the plaine and naked truth muſt then come in place, and we ſhalbe enforced to giue our account, euery one of vs by our ſelues.</p>
            <p>This is the principall matter that muſt be done before the Iudge,<note place="margin">We muſt giue accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> that we muſt giue account of our ſelues, and of our deedes done in this life. And moſt ſhall haue ſorrowfull hearts, becauſe they ſhalbe called to their accounts. As it was ſaid to the euill ſteward, <hi>Come giue account of thy ſtewarſhip:</hi> ſo ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of vs be called to our account, haue vſed thoſe benefites, gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150982:24"/>which God hath endued vs withall; whether to Gods glory, and to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of other, or after our owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and to the hurt of others. In the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Romaines, Chap. 14.10.12 <hi>We ſhall all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Christ; and then euery one of us, ſhall giue accounts of himſelfe to God.</hi> The wicked which lightly ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be brought to any accounts, they ſhal giue accounts to him that is ready to iudge quick and dead. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.5. Not only moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wicked deedes ſhalbe called to account, but we ſhall giue a reckoning for euery idle word. So we read, <hi>Math.</hi> 12.36. <hi>Out of the good treaſure of the heart, we bring forth good. But I ſay vnto you</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that of euery idle word, that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſtall giue account thereof, at the day of Iudgement.</hi> When as wee ſhall aunſwere for our ſelues, beeing altogether vnable to aunſwere one for a thouſand. Yea ſo much the more grieuous it ſhall bee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee ſhall open all the ſecrets of our heart, and bee enforced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our miſdeeds, and to keepe backe nothing, all muſt bee manifeſt.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150982:24"/>
            <p>And not as it is in this world, when vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the humble confeſſion of our ſinnes to God, wee may cry for pardon; and hope to be forgiuen; but then ſhall but confeſſion be; to our open ſhame, confuſion, and endleſſe deſtruction. Wherefore this day of iudgement, may well bee called the day of Reuelation, when as all things that are now hid, ſhall then be reuealed and made known.<note place="margin">Secrets opened.</note> Here on earth, many things are kept cloſe, hid and hudled vp <hi>But God ſhall tigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> faith the Apoſtle, <hi>things that are hid in darkneſſe:</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>and make the counſels of the heart manifest. And at that day; Ro.</hi> 2.16. <hi>God ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Christ.</hi> In this life, many great and ſinfull deedes are not puniſhed, but remaine hid and vnknowne, and the parties paſſe as guiloleſſe, and without all faulte, who thinke themſelues cleare inough, ſo long as they can keepe their owne counſell. But our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>Luke.</hi> 8.17. ſheweth the matter to be cleane contrary. <hi>Nothing is ſecret that ſhall not bee euident; neyther any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150982:25"/>thing hid, that ſhall not be knowne and come to light.</hi> The which in <hi>Eccle.</hi> 12.14. is more manifeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>God will bring eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worke vnto iudgement, with euery ſecret thing, whether it be good or euill.</hi> Which is not ſet downe to driue vs to diſpaire: although no doubt we are priuie to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hainous ſinnes the which we would not for all the worlds good, ſhould bee knowne abroade, and in euery mans mouth: yea &amp; ſuch ſin that are forcible inough, to driue vs to diſpaire yet ſeeing at the iudgement day, they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, be they neuer ſo ſecret, wee are moued hereby, to call for mercy, while God doth graunt vs life; and to pray with the Prophet: <hi>O Lord deliuer mee from my ſecret faults, from my ſecret ſinnes, from my ſecret offences.</hi> This therefore that our ſecret hidden faults, ſhall come to light &amp; iudgement, is a very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leſſon for vs, whereby we may learn to feare what we do, although wee may keepe it cloſe from men: as alſo that we may bethinke our ſelues of that which is paſt, and pray for forgiueneſſe, and be more warie and circumſpect in time to come: ſo that it keepeth vs in the feare
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150982:25"/>of God, ſo long as we liue: and let this be vnto vs, in ſtead of <hi>Auricular confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> in remembrance whereof, in euery time and place, wee may flye and auoyd all ſinne, whether it be ſecret or open, whereof if we take not heed, we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the daunger of Gods wrath and heauy iudgement. And at the day of iudgement, ſhall God bring all matters to light, as we may read, <hi>Reue.</hi> 20.12. <hi>And I ſawe the dead both great and ſmall ſtand before God: and the bookes were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> (that is their conſcience) <hi>and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther booke was opened, which is the booke of life. And the dead were iudged of thoſe things which were written in the bookes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not onely God,<note place="margin">Conſcience</note> that ſhall bring our ſecret ſinnes to light, but euen our owne conſciences ſhall bewray vs, as the laſt place of Scripture alleadged. <hi>Reue.</hi> 20.12. dooth teſtifie, where by the bookes that were opened, our owne conſciences are vnderſtood, which ſhall be moſt ready to reueale all things. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that in the Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, Chap. 2.15. <hi>Which ſhew the effect of the law written in their hearts, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150982:26"/>alſo bearing witneſſe, and theyr thoughts accuſing one another, or excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, at that day, when God ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Christ.</hi> And full truly is it ſpoken, that a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is in ſteed of a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. For when time ſhall ſerue, there ſhall not neede many accuſers, or ſtore of euidences to be giuen vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, ſeeing that our conſcience which is our ſecret ſtorehoue, ſhall declare all, although it bee neuer ſo much againſt our will; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraint or compariſon. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue a ſufficient and manifeſt try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, euen in this life.</p>
            <p>For tell me, who is it among vs, but muſt of force confeſſe, and dooth perceiue ſo much in himſelfe, that hee cannot, no nor may not forget his ſinnes and miſdeedes, for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will not ſuffer it; and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the more notorious, bad and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, our deedes haue beene, the more freſh and freſh they are, and will bee in our remembrance. They will come into our mindes, when wee little thinke of any ſuch matter: and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150982:26"/>if wee would neuer ſo faine, wee cannot put them away from vs, and when they come into our mindes and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, they bring dumps and ſorrow inough. Which is a token and a moſt apparant ſigne and proofe, of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, vnto the which time all our ſinnes are reſerued to bee iudged. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we commit any wicked or notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deed, our conſcience within vs doth grudge againſt it, and would full faine bridle and reſtraine vs from it, if it were poſſible: but after wee haue done the deed, it is a torment vnto vs, and that more grieuous inwardly to our mindes, then any whip or ſcourge to the body can bee, becauſe the one is but for a time, the other laſteth long and ſhall endure. By which inward griefe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, and ſorrowe of conſcience, many are driuen to diſpaire, and doo thinke ſo bad of themſelues, for theyr wicked, vnlawful, &amp; vngodly deeds, that they are deſirous to reuenge the matter vpon themſelues, and to be their owne tormenters, before the iudgement day come. But if there be any that can ſay, their conſcience is cleare, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioyce,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150982:27"/>and giue God the praiſe and thankes, who hath preuented them with his grace, and preſerued them from euill. And as a guiltie conſcience is his owne tormenter, ſo a good conſcience is a continuall feaſt. He or ſhee that is not charged, or rather ouercharged by their owne conſcience, they haue a continuall ioy within them: ſo if our owne hearts condemne vs, God is greater then our hearts, and knoweth all things. And what miſerie trowe we, doo the wicked of the world liue in? For the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>There is no peace vnto the wicked;</hi> when in all their life, is feare and terror; carrying in their breaſts tormenting fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to hold them day &amp; night, in feare of endleſſe deſtruction. And what ſhould thoſe heauy dumps and inward feares ſignifie, but that there is a iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that there is a hell, as well as a heauen. Their hearts doo droope, and their conſciences are affrighted, and God by his ſecret power dooth worke this feare: and no doubt they feele that there is giuen to them a ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and feare, through which they tremble at their owne eſtate. They are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150982:27"/>in mount <hi>Sinay:</hi> where is the burning fire, blackneſſe, darkneſſe, tempeſt, and the ſound of a Trumpet, in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof, they tremble and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly tormented.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay, the wicked proſper, and reioyce in their dayes, they are bound in no ſuch bondage, nor feare no ſuch feare. Thou canſt not tell, neither doeſt thou know, the heart of wicked man, howſoeuer hee boaſt in his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and outward proſperitie, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to haue peace, peraduenture there is a bitter remembrance within him, of the iudgement to come. He may delight and ſport himſelfe, but in that laughing the heart is ſorrowfull, and that myrth doth end in heauineſſe. And albeit they ſtriue maruellouſly, to caſt out this feare, yet if they could caſt it out from them, as out of a cannon and field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peece, yet would it euermore returne vnto them againe, and vexe their heart, that ſo flyeth from it. If they would full faine ſeare vp their conſciences, as with a hot and glowing Iron, yet ſometime it will awake them, as out of a ſleepe, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aht vpon a ſudden, they ſhall ſee a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150982:28"/>ſight of death and iudgement. And as we read, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. <hi>That the feruent deſire of the creature wayteth, when the ſonnes of God ſhall be reuealed:</hi> ſo alſo we may well ſay, that the conſciences of men, do groane as it were, vnder the burthen of ſinne, and earneſtly deſire to be di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>burthened, and yet they ſhall not. For at the iudgement day, when all the creatures of the earth ſhall haue their deſire, then ſhall the conſciences of the wicked torment them a freſh, and that more fiercely then euer they did before. For then ſhall the time be, that we ſhall giue account, and God ſhall bring all our ſecret ſinnes to light, our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bearing witneſſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The diuell ſhall accuſe</note>And yet there remaineth an other accuſer, beſide God and our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and that is the diuell, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſought our deſtruction, and brought vs vnto it, by diuers temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſugered baytes. The diuel ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be at hand to accuſe vs, to call for iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt vs, who after our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is giuen, and the ſentence paſt, ſhalbe ready moſt terribly to torment vs, world without end. And to bring
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150982:28"/>this to paſſe, then ſhall he lay deeply to our charge, and call for iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, reioycing and triumphing that he hath ſo good a cauſe before ſo righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous a Iudge, earneſtly crauing that hee will iudge vprightly, becauſe iuſtice and iudgement is the preparation of his ſeat, and his throne is eſtabliſhed by it. I pray thee therefore, will this accuſer ſay, giue ſentence with me, and iudge him to bee mine, which while hee liued would be none of thine: mine he or ſhe whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is by right, and they haue deſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erued to ſuffer torments with me: and ſeeing they haue followed my wayes in theyr liues, now let them be partakers of my puniſhments. And ſhall not the Iudge of the world doo right ſaith <hi>Abraham,</hi> and miniſter righteous iudgement? yea doubtleſſe, as the Apoſtle S. <hi>Iude verſ.</hi> 14. hath ſet it downe. <hi>Behold the Lord commeth with thouſands of Saints, to giue iudgement againſt all men, and to rebuke all the vngodly among them, of all their wicked deeds which they haue vngodly committed, and of all their cruell ſpeakings, which wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſinners haue ſpoken againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When all matters are thus made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150982:29"/>all ſhall be iudged, partly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the confeſſion of their owne guiltie conſcience, and partly by the word of God, which they haue hard, and which they haue either neglected or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed: euen by the ſelfeſame word ſhal they be iudged. For by that ſhall they be made without excuſe, and the more culpable before Gods iudgement ſeate. As we may reade in the Goſpell of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Word.</note> Chap. 12.48. <hi>He that refuſeth me, and receiueth not my words, hath one that iudgeth him: the word that I haue ſpoken, it ſhall iudge him in the laſt day.</hi> Where by the way we are taught, to haue the more regard of the word of God, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to heare it, with remembrance to keepe it in our hearts, and with care to expreſſe it in our liues and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it may be a helpe to our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereas otherwiſe it is like to bee our Iudge to our condemnation. Which is further declared by that which is ſet downe; <hi>Acts</hi> 13.40.41. <hi>Beware there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaſt that come vpon you, which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the Prophets: Behold the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and wonder, and vaniſh away: For I worke a worke in their dayes, a work which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150982:29"/>yee ſhall not beleeue, if a man would declare it vnto you.</hi> Which worke by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the learned, is the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vengeance of God, vpon thoſe that contemne his word.</p>
            <p>Thus then beeing in his preſence, and after the generall trial of our cauſe, and after we haue giuen our account, ſhall Ieſus Chriſt, who is appointed to be the Iudge of quick and dead, proceed to Iudgement; in ſeperating the iuſt from the vniuſt, the good from the bad, the wheat from the chaffe, the ſheepe from the goates. For in this world they are mingled together, the good with bad, and God ſuffereth his raine to fall, as well vpon the vniuſt as the iuſt; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he haſty to ſeparat them, the one from the other in this life: To the end that he may ſhewe his patience toward the wicked, in giuing them time and ſpace to repent; as alſo by their meanes, he exerciſeth his Church and people, to teach them patience, and to try whether they will ſtand ſtedfaſt vnto him, or fall away from him, with the reſt of the world. And as he rebuked his Diſciples, becauſe they deſired that fire ſhould
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150982:30"/>come downe from heauen to conſume the Samaritanes; ſo alſo he findeth fault with them, that would haue a ſeperation before the iuſt time come. According as we read in the Epiſtle to the Romans, Chap. 12.19. <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay it</hi> ſaith the Lord. God knoweth his iuſt time: and his appointed time, is the end of the world. Which matter is very effectually ſet downe in a Parable, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.12. For after the good feede was ſowne, and the blade ſproong vp and brought forth fruite, then appeared alſo tares. <hi>Then came the ſeruants of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, and ſaid vnto the maiſter: Maiſter, ſowedſt not thou good ſeed in thy field? from whence then hath it tares? And hee ſaid to them, the enuious man hath done this. Then the ſeruants ſaid vnto him; Wilt thou then, that we goe and gather them vp? But hee ſaid nay; leaſt while ye go about to gather the tares, yee pluck vp alſo with them the wheat. Let both grow together, vntill the harueſt, and in time of harueſt, I will ſay to the reapers, gather ye firſt the tares, and bind them in ſheaues to burne them, but ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wheat into my barne.</hi> The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore may comfort themſelues
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150982:30"/>with this, that in time to come, though not preſently and out of hand, there ſhalbe a ſeperation. The kingdome of heauen is likened vnto a drawe net, caſt into the ſea, that gathereth of all kindes of things: <hi>which when it is full, men draw to land, and ſit and gather the good into veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and caſt the bad away: So ſhall it bee at the end of the world; the good and the bad ſhall be parted:</hi> after that the trumpet hath blowne, and the dead bee rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Againe the ſeed ſowne, is the word of God preached: <hi>The field wherein it is ſowne, is the world; the good ſeed are they which with an honeſt heart, heare the word and keep it, and bring forth fruite, and theſe be the children of the Kingdome: and the tares are the children of the wicked, and the enemie that ſoweth them, is the diuell: and the harueſt is the end of the world, and the reapers be the Angels. As then the tares are gathered and brent in the fire, ſo ſhall it be in the end of the world. The ſonne of man ſhall ſend forth his Angels, and they ſhal ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they ſhall ſeperate. Math.</hi> 13.39. When the regions and parts of the earth are white, then is the time of harueſt. As we read in the <hi>Reue.</hi> 14.15. <hi>That the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150982:31"/>Angel cried with a loud voyce to him that ſate on the cloud; Thrust in thy ſickle and reape, for the time is come to reape, for the harueſt of the earth is ripe.</hi> As though he ſaw the time when the number of Gods elect and choſen children, ſhould bee fulfilled, and the ſinnes of the vngodly and wicked, come to a full meaſure. <hi>And the Angel thruſt in his ſharpe ſickle on the earth, and cut downe the vines of the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the earth, and cast them into the great Wine-preſſe of the wrath of God.</hi> So ſhall the bad bee ſeperated from the good, as a ſhepheard ſeperateth the ſheepe from the goates: and the Iudge, who is meant by the ſhepheard, ſhall commaund the ſheepe to be ſet on his right hand, and the goates on the left, the good and the bad. And then will hee addreſſe himſelfe to giue ſententence, and to take order for the execution of his iudgement.</p>
            <p>And who ſhall ſtay or hinder this iudgement?<note place="margin">Sentence.</note> or who ſhall auoyd the fierceneſſe &amp; furiouſneſſe of his wrath? Shall the king be deliuered by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of an hoſt? No, he ſhalbe but as one man, naked and vnarmed, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150982:31"/>helpe; and hee that ſhall come to iudge him, commeth with infinite thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Angels. The ſtrength of the ſtrong man ſhall then ſtand him in no ſtead, but in ſtead of ſtrength, he ſhall bee reſolued into feare and weakneſſe. The wealth of the rich man ſhall not ranſome him: for riches ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in the day of wrath. Before ſo wiſe, ſo vpright, ſuch a Iudge, of that courage thou ſhalt ſtand, whom neither feare ſhall daunt, nor fauour ſhall moue, nor gold ſhal bribe and corrupt him, neither any entreaty or prayer, then at that time ſhall perſwade him. There ſhalbe no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, no falſifying of the cauſe, no colours nor excuſe to blinde him; no learning, no men of lawe ſhall defend thee: no wit nor pollicie ſhall go beyond this Iudge: no ſpeech nor flattery ſhall preuaile with him: in a word, what ſhall worldly helpes doo, when the world it ſelf ſhal vaniſh awaye Nothing that ſhall be deuiſed ſhall turn his mind, nothing ſhall alter or reuerſe his iudgement, it ſhall paſſe without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, and without all reuocation. For then ſhall hee come to iudge the world
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150982:32"/>righteouſly, and to miniſter true iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto the people.</p>
            <p>And thus after that the ſheepe be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from the goates, ſhall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be executed, and ſentence ſhall be giuen, in ſuch ſort and order, as we read it ſet down, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. <hi>Then ſhal the king, that is the Iudge ſay to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on his right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; Come ye bleſſed of my father inherit yee the kingdome prepared for you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the world</hi> But to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on his left hand, he ſhal ſay; <hi>Depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ye curſed into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting fire, which is preparêd for the diuell and his angels. And theſe ſhall go into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting pain, and the righteous into life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi> By reaſon of which fearefull ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, the wicked ſhall haue good cauſe to ſay to the mountaines, and to the Rocks, <hi>Reue.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Fall on vs, and hide vs from the preſence of him that ſitteth on the throne, and from the wrath of the lambe. For the great day of his wrath is come, and who can ſtand?</hi> They ſhall deſire to hide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in dens, &amp; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Rocks and mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, but yet ſhal they not auoid his preſence: they ſhal deſire death, &amp; ſhall not find it; &amp; ſeeke after it, and yet ſhall death fly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. And as the diuels (as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150982:32"/>we read in the Goſpell) beſought Chriſt that he would not torment them before their time, ſo now ſhal the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wrath of God be, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diuels, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue either forgotten, or not regarded, and highly diſpleaſed God, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter hazard of their ſoules, ſhalbe caſt into hell, and throwne into endleſſe torments. And therefore ſhall his comming be in flaming fire, to render vengeance againſt the ſinners of the earth: who not onely ſhall be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the preſence of God, and from the glory of his power, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the bleſſed Angels, and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſoules; but that which is far worſe, and more grieuous and lamentable, they ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and deſtruction. And the Angels that ſeperat the good from the bad, ſhal then gather out of his kingdome all things that offend, and them which do iniquitie, and ſhall caſt them into a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of fire, there ſhall be wailing and gnaſhing of teeth. <hi>When as the iust and godly ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their father:</hi> and when the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed ſort ſhall go downe by a by way.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150982:33"/>a backe way and a blacke, with many a ſigh and ſob from God, from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, from the Saints, from ioy, from glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, from bliſſe: with the fiends of Hell, to ſuppe in the pallace of darkneſſe with the princes of horror, at the table of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, in the chaire of calamitie, with the crowne of death vpon their head, hauing nothing before their eyes, but infinite torments prepared for them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the ſentence pronounced and laſt iudgement giuen,<note place="margin">How this iudgement pertaineth to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and to the wicked.</note> an entrance is laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto me, to declare vnto you, how this iudgement pertaineth to the wicked and vnto the godly, which was the laſt thing, in this treatiſe of the latter iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I purpoſed to ſpeake vnto you of. Vnto the which, I haue thought good to adde an exhortation, that wee may be prepared againſt the time, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing oyle in our lampes, with the fiue wiſe virgines, that waited for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the bridegrome.</p>
            <p>It is an article of our beliefe, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not without ſingular comfort and commoditie, that he that vouchſafed to take our nature vpon him, and to bee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150982:33"/>cloathed with our fleſh; that ſuffered and endured the ſpitefull dealing of the wicked, and an accurſed death for our ſakes: that he that roſe from death to bring vs to life; that he that aſcended into heauen to procure vs an entrance into his fathers Kingdome, and to make vs fellow heires with himſelfe: that he I ſay, would not forſake vs, euen in the moſt dreadfull time and greateſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, when we had deſerued the heauy ſentence of iudgement, and wofull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. That hee would ſet vs free from all feare, and to haue that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and moſt gracious regard of vs, as though we had neuer offended him, and to vſe this chearefull and ioyfull ſpeech vnto vs, <hi>Come ye bleſſed.</hi> I ſay this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is not without ſingular comfort, <hi>From thence ſhall be come to iudge both the quicke and the dead.</hi> Which is not ſpoken to the wicked, to whom nothing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, but onely the vanities and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this tranſitorie life, which ſhall haue an end, and a ſudden end, and a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and heauy recompence: but to the comfort of the godly, and to encourage them, which haue ſighed and groaned
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150982:34"/>vnder the burthen of their ſinnes, and who haue fledde vnto the throne of the grace of God, and holding out a godly courſe, haue through hope and patience, looked for this deliuerance, which ſhall be at the day of doome and iudgement. Which comming of Chriſt vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhalbe vnto them, as the appearing of the Angel was, after Chriſt his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the women, that is milde and gentle, <hi>Be not ye affraid, let not your hearts be troubled.</hi> But vnto the reſt, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſhall be like lightning, <hi>and hee ſhal come in flaming fire, re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring vengeance.</hi> So that they ſhall not be onely aſtonied, and become as dead men, as were the ſouldiers, that were ſet to keepe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt in the graue: but further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, they ſhall be in horrible feare and trembling. And happy were they, if they might be partakers of their deſire ſo far, as not to be, &amp; to become as thogh they had neuer bene borne. But as the godly do paſſe to ioyes, ſo the other of force muſt liue in eternall torments. In conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of which iudgement, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to come, they leade a life conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in feare, and tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150982:34"/>of their woful eſtate, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhalbe.</p>
            <p>The godly alſo haue good cauſe to feare the ſelfeſame feare of the laſt iudgement and eternall torments, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their manifold ſinnes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, whereby they haue prouoked the heauy wrath of God againſt them. But that they might be raiſed vp againe and comforted, it pleaſed our Sauiour Chriſt to receiue the ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation himſelfe, and againſt his owne perſon (hee beeing altogether innocent and guiltleſſe) in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and from the mouth of an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Iudge, <hi>Pontius Pilat</hi> by name; that wee might bee acquitted and ſet free, at the terrible and fearefull day of iudgement, which in the ende of the world ſhall come vpon all fleſh; that wee I ſay, might bee acquitted which are altogether full of ſinnes, and altogether guiltie. According to that we read. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Now then there is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> And what ſhall we then ſay? <hi>If God be on our ſide, who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be againſt vs? who ſpared not his own ſon, but gaue him for vs al to death: how
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150982:35"/>ſhall he not with him giue vs all things alſo? who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? It is God that iuſtifieth, who ſhall condemne? It is Chriſt which is dead, yea or rather which is riſen againe, who is alſo at the right hand of God, &amp; maketh requ<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſt alſo for vs.</hi> So that I may boldly ſay to them, who feele the inward comfort of Gods ſpirit within their hearts, by the forgiueneſſe of their ſinnes through Chriſt his death: Feare not this feare, nor tremble as the wicked doo at this iudgement. For ſeeing ye are led by the good ſpirit of God, it is a token that yee are the children of God, and that yee haue not receiued the ſpirit of bondage to feare againe; but ye haue receiued the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> which is as much as to ſay father, euen our father which art in heauen. And the ſame ſpirit of God beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that wee are the children of God: and if we be children, wee are alſo heires, euen the heires of God, and fellowe heires with Chriſt our elder brother. Wherefore there is no cauſe why the godly ſhould feare this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the wicked feare it. For as the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150982:35"/>one ſort ſhall at that day receiue the iudgement of condemnation, whereof they haue an inward feeling in this life, which makes them feare; ſo the other ſhall receiue the ſentence of abſolution, and ſhall bee quit as it were by procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when Chriſt ſhall ſay, <hi>Come yee bleſſed.</hi> Which is the cauſe that moueth the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 4.17. to breake forth into theſe words: <hi>Herein is the loue of God perfect toward vs, that we ſhould haue boldneſſe at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Therefore the godly make their prayers, and wiſh that this day might come ſhortly, <hi>Reue.</hi> 22. <hi>Come Lord Ieſus come quickly.</hi> The wicked would not haue it come as yet: nay, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they could wiſh it ſhould neuer be, and that it would neuer come to paſſe. Torment vs not, ſay the diuels to Chriſt, before our time: Oh ſay the wicked, that this time might neuer be, or that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, wee might vaniſh away and come to nothing. How greatly auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſhall it be to the godly, when hee that is their Sauiour, and hath ſhead his moſt precious bloud for their redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: hee that is their elder brother, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150982:36"/>hath purchaſed vnto them this libertie, as to be called the ſonnes of God; when he that is their head, and hath made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his members, ſhalbe their Iudge to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, and to declare them righteous; and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n at that day hee ſhall deliuer them from all ſinne, feare of death, the diuell, hell, and all other miſeries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with other ſhall not onely be ouertaken but ouerwhelmed. For who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? and who ſhall procure their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, whoſe ſaluation God hath wrought? But to the great terrour of the godleſſe and wicked, who feare not God, nor loue either Chriſt or his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, hee ſhall be their Iudge, to their fearefull and that moſt iuſt deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>This alſo ſhal not onely be an inward refreſhing, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g great miſeries, wrongs, and perſecutions, while wee liue heere on the earth, but alſo a great ioy in time to come, that al vnrighteous iudgement ſhall be called to account, and that there ſhalbe a generall and moſt abſolute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. For on earth, for the moſt part, there is no true iudgement, as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150982:36"/>though the iudgement ſeate were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the defence and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of them, not that are oppreſſed, but that do oppreſſe: not for the reliefe and ſuccour of them that are wronged, but to countenance and bolſter them out, who as the Propher ſaith, deuiſe miſchiefe vpon their beds, and practiſe it when they come abroad. Therefore <hi>Salomon, Eccle.</hi> 5.7. giueth inſtruction to the godly, that they be not mooued, and that they may be confirmed in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, looking for a day of hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing. <hi>If in a countrey</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou ſeeſt the oppreſſion of the poore, &amp; the defrauding of iudgement and iustice, bee not astonied at the matter, and maruell not; for hee that is higher then the higheſt regardeth, and there bee higher then they.</hi> Whereby they are put in mind, both of a more vpright Iudge, then is no earth to be ſeene; and of a more righteous iudgement, by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and force whereof, they ſhalbe both righted and relieued. Concerning which matter, <hi>Eſdras</hi> hath ſpoken very well, 2. <hi>Eſd.</hi> 7.32. <hi>The earth ſhall reſtore thoſe that haue ſlept in her, and the most high ſhall appeare vpon the ſeate of iudgement;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150982:37"/>and miſeries ſhall vaniſh away, and long ſuffering ſhall haue an end: iustice onely ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue; the truth ſhall remain, and vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſhall beare no more rule.</hi> For the wicked thinketh not on the iudgement to come; nay the are inwardly blinded, and that by Gods ſecret appointment, being ſo farre giuen vp to their owne luſts, that they care not what villanie or violence they put in practice. But the godly are willed to haue regard to this rightfull day, when true iudgement ſhal onely haue the vpper hand: againe they muſt take heed, that when they ſuffer, they ſuffer not as euill doers and male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors; for then they cannot looke for redreſſe an other day, and then this earthly iudgement dooth lawfully take place againſt them. But in all well doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let euery one commend this ſoule to God, and commit his cauſe to that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudge. This laſt iudgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is for the benefite of the godly, that it may go well with them, whoſe cauſe in this life could not be heard, nor any iuſtice done them. Againe, that not onely they may be righted in their cauſe, but alſo that they may bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150982:37"/>from that infamy, and from thoſe ſpitefull and approbrious ſpeeches, which the world hath giuen out againſt them: dooing them more hurt and wrong, and inward griefe thereby, then by falſe iudgement which hath paſſed againſt them, and whereby they haue had their willes of them, and haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed. And as the reſtoring of theyr righteous cauſe, and of their credit and good name, which the world hath la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to depriue them of, ſhall be an occaſion of Chriſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo alſo is the condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked. For in this life their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is begun, their conſcience witneſſing againſt them, which then, and at the iudgement day, ſhall fully and perfectly be declared; which is not ſpoken, that the godly are cleare from iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by their deſert: for they are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and offenders, as others, though not perhaps in the ſame degree. Who through repentance and a liuely faith, taking hold of the mercies of God, haue no need to feare this iudgement, becauſe God doth not impute their ſinnes vnto them; and alſo their conſciences do in
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150982:38"/>this ſort declare them free: although in reſpect of themſelues, they are greatly guilty. So that Chriſt ſhal ſtand on their ſide, and their conſcience ſhall witneſſe vnto them, the exceeding loue of God and his gracious meercies, which ſhalbe the breath of life vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; an aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ioyes. But the wicked becauſe they haue their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences accuſing and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; the fierce cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of the Iudge to daunt them, and fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſmay them; the diuel pleading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and calling for iudgement to be done vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: therefore are they to look for nothing elſe, but euen the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; the fearful ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation: which ſhal make them as it were to fall in peeces, through qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king &amp; trembling, and to be reſolued to nothing: but that by Gods appointment they are reſerued to euerlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, together with the diuell &amp; his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Who alſo I mean the diuell and his angels ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by the ſentence of Gods ſeuere iudgement, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue highly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded god, but alſo becauſe they haue bene the authors of the ruine &amp; downfall of all mankind,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150982:38"/>in prouoking and tempting them to all diſobedience, ſin &amp; miſchiefe. When as the righteous ſhall liue for euer, &amp; ſhall receiue a glorious kingdome, &amp; a bewti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full crowne at the Lords hand. Chriſt ſhall come again the ſecond time, as it is <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.3. and ſhal receiue vs vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that where he is, there may we be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And as it is ſaid of our Sauiour Chriſt, to the manifeſtation of his great glory, that they ſhall then ſee him, whom they haue pierced through: whoſe preſence, ſhall be to the greater confuſion of the wicked &amp; his enemies, who ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to behold him to be their iudge, and to abide his iudgement, whom they haue in this life ſo greatly deſpiſed, &amp; ſo cruelly handled: ſo alſo ſhal Chriſt make his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers the godly, repentant, &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full partakers of this his glory, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath promiſed. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. <hi>That they ſhal ſit vpon twelue thrones, and iudge the twelue Tribes of</hi> Iſrael: not that they ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be Iudges, but that they ſhal approue his iudgement. A ſhadow wherof, we haue in theſe our earthly iudgements, whereas you ſee the iuſtices &amp; men of account, ſit with the Iudge, not that they haue to do with pronouncing ſentence, or with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150982:39"/>the iudgement, but that amongſt the reſt, it is a token vnto them, of honour and dignitie, in the ſight of the people. According to the which meaning, wee read, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.28. <hi>That there ſhalbe wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnaſhing of teeth, when the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall ſee</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob: (meaning thereby, they godly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) <hi>and all the prophets in the kingdome of God, and themſelues thruſt out at doores,</hi> and heauen gates ſhut againſt them: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that taking as the rich man was, ſpoken of in the Goſpell, who being in hell, beheld <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, himſelfe crying out but for one drop of cold water, to allay that bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vnquenchable heate, which he found himſelfe to be in, and could not haue it. Then ſhall they begin to ſay with themſelues, when they ſhall ſee the righteous ſtand in great boldneſſe, ſo that they ſhall be vexed with horrible feare, and wonderfully amazed, then ſhall they chaunge their mindes, and ſigh with inward gitefe, and ſay within themſelues; <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5. <hi>Theſe are they, whom ſometime we had in deriſion,</hi> (as indeede who are more derided and contemned
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150982:39"/>in the world, then they that be well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and to their power liue after the feare of God) <hi>Theſe are they, whom wee had in deriſion, &amp; in a parable of reproach. We fooles thought their liues madneſſe, and their end without honor. But now how is it, that they are counted among the children of God, and that their prouiſion is among the the Saints:</hi> and that they are ſo highly in Gods fauour? <hi>Therefore we haue erred from the way of truth, and the light of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe hath not ſhined vnto vs: and the Sunne of vnderſtanding roſe not vpon vs. We haue wearied our ſelues in the way of wickedneſſe and deſtruction, and we haue gone through daungerous wayes, but wee haue not knowne the way of the Lord,</hi> nor liued in his feare.</p>
            <p>And now hauing heard the chiefeſt matters concerning the day of doome, and the generall and laſt day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that wee may the better bee prepared vnto it, let vs heare what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is giuen vs, in holy ſcriptures. And firſt, that of the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> may take place, and ſeemeth greatly to tend to this purpoſe. Which counſell wee read, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. in this ſort. If wee
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150982:40"/>would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not be iudged: and this profit wee ſhould reape thereby, that in time to come, we ſhould not be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned with the world. But as a matter full of terror and pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiueneſſe, wee will not enter into ſo deepe a conſideration, nor trouble our conſciences ſo farre; as to iudge our ſelues, or to fall into examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our owne wayes. Whereas no doubt if wee ſhould ſo doo, it would fall out moſt happily on our ſide. For if vpon due try all and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, without all partiallitie and affection, wee ſhould pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of iudgement againſt our ſelues, according to our deſerts, it would bee no otherwiſe, nor no better then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And yet not that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation which woorketh diſpaire, but ſuch a condemnation whereby wee might bee acquitted from euerlaſting condemnation. As the ſame Apoſtle writing to the Corinthians, 2. <hi>Cor. 7.9. I now reioyce</hi> ſaith he, <hi>not that yee were ſory, but that yee ſorrowed to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For yee ſorrowed godly, ſo that in nothing ye were hurt by vs. For
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150982:40"/>godly ſorrowe cauſeth repentance vnto ſaluation, not to bee repented of; but the worldly ſorrowe, cauſeth death.</hi> So verily, if wee would enter into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with our ſelues, it would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a griefe and ſorrowe; but ſuch a ſorrowe (eſpecially if it came from a well meaning minde) that ſhould not be vnto death. For by iudging of our ſelues, we ſhould take a viewe of that death, and of thoſe torments, which by reaſon of our ſinnes we deſerue. And by this meane, we ſhould be driuen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and to ſeeke after God; to bee reconciled vnto God, &amp; to returne into his fauour: that our conſciences might be disburthened of ſo great feare, which the ſeuerity of the laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god, might work within vs, &amp; that we might haue boldneſſe and comfort in that day. But if we walke on ſecurely &amp; careleſly, and wil not once vouchſafe to enter into iudgement with our ſelues, then may we a while be merry in this world, but our mirth ſhal hereafter be turned into mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. As the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth put ſuch care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe perſons in remembrance, that in their iollitie, they might not too much forget themſelues.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:150982:41"/>
            <p>Reioyce ſaith he, if ſo be, it ſeeme good in thine eyes, but remember therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that thou ſhalt be called to account and to iudgement. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 11.9. and 12.14. And therefore he giueth this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, Chap. 7.14. <hi>It is better to go to the houſe of mourning, then to the houſe of fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Anger is better then laughter; for by a ſad looke the heart is made the better.</hi> Better it is to be in the houſe of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to weepe for our ſinnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are in daunger of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to be in the houſe of feaſting and forgetfulneſſe, to enioy ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with the world for a ſmall time, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our life is but as a ſpan long, &amp; that here onely, and in this life, is the time of forgiueneſſe, that we may be pardoned. Better it is to be angry with our ſelues, then to pleaſe our ſelues in ſuch ſort: and a ſad minde is a meane and a great help to further our repentance. And how ſhall we obtaine ſo godly a purpoſe as to bee ſet free from Gods heauy anger, which we haue moſt iuſtly deſerued, if we doo not vſe the meanes which tend therevnto? Commonly where iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, there followeth condemnation:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150982:41"/>but heare how ſweete and comfortable it is, that in iudging of our ſelues after this order, which I haue ſet downe vnto you, we ſhall find a way to be quit from euerlaſting condemnation. Which we can no way eſcape, if in this life wee doo not iudge our ſelues and condemne our ſelues, by true repentance; calling for mercie and forgiueneſſe, that wee may be receiued into Gods fauour, and not in time to come, to be condemned with the world. For in ſo iudging of our ſelues, it is not a meanes to cauſe vs to diſpaire, but to haue a better hope, and an enduring, and a reioycing comfort: which comfort, ſhall neuer bee taken from vs, if ſtill wee be mindfull to call our ſelues to iudgement, and haue an eye to our wayes, that wee do not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let euery one of vs pray, that our hearts may bee ſo prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this iudgement day, that we may be moſt willing to call our ſelues to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and to iudgement. So that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thus humbled our ſelues, after a while all feare ſhall paſſe away from vs, and our hearts ſhall be filled with ioy;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150982:42"/>and whereas heretofore we haue wiſhed that this day ſhould not bee, now wee ſhall deſire in heart to haue it come to paſſe. And ſo much the more, becauſe our conſciences ſhall aſſure vs, (our ſins being forgiuen) that we ſhall not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the number of them, that ſhall be condemned, but among them to whom it ſhall be ſaid, <hi>Come yee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, inherit the kingdome prepared for you.</hi> Which comfortable words, God graunt we may then heare, to our euerlaſting comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Spend the time in an honeſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note>An other remedy to auoyd the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of this puniſhment is, to ſeeke to pleaſe God in this world, in an honeſt vocation and trade of life. For as idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the cauſe of many ſinnes and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo godly painfulneſſe is the mother of all vertues: and which doth breede a great comfort to our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, againſt the time when we ſhall be called to our account, how we haue ſpent our time, and imployed thoſe good gifts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath inabled vs.</p>
            <p>Therefore in the Goſpell, before the declaration of the latter day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there is mention made of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150982:42"/>that were beſtowed, &amp; they that receiued them, were called to the recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, how they employed them: the ſlothfull being bound hand and foote, and caſt into vtter darkneſſe, and the painfull highly aduanced. So that there is a way offered to auoyd iudgement, and they that are therein negligent and careleſſe, ſhall be guilty of iudgement: and ſhall fall into diuers miſchiefes and ſins, which ſhal make them more faulty, and worthy of greater condemnation. The life of man ſomewhere is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a warfare, becauſe wee ought to fight with it, and to reſiſt all euill tentations. So alſo is it wel compared to marchandiſe, becauſe we ought alwayes to be painfull, according as God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. The marchant increaſeth the wealth and honor of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-weale, and hath wherwithal he may be liberal vnto others, &amp; rich vnto himſelf. In like ſort, hath God created vs to his honour, and that by that vocation, whervnto he hath called vs, we ſhuld ſet forth his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: &amp; as we are borne to the benefit one of an other, ſo in our vocation, ought we to do good to al, as much as lyeth in our power.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:150982:43"/>
            <p>And by the performance of our dutie, according to Gods commaundement, we ſhall be able to aſſure our ſelues of Gods fauour and bleſſing towards vs. Let vs redeeme the time ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, for no dout we haue ſpent much of our time euilly. And ſo redeeming the time, that is granted vs in honeſt, vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and godly affaires and exerciſes, we ſhalbe kept from wicked rhoughts, ydle words, and ſhamefull deedes, whereby we are made guiltie of Gods wrath and heauy iudgement.</p>
            <p>A wonder it is to ſee, that many to whom God hath giuen excellent gifts, do leaſt vſe them, eyther to Geds glory, or the benefite of their countrey. Yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are giuen to abuſe them, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them to the diſhonour of God, and to the hurt of others, and to the ſhame of themſelues. And I would to God, this might come into their mindes, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom, and vpon whom, God hath beſtowed much, much alſo of them ſhal be required. Many I ſay, withdrawe themſelues from doing good, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the good gifts of GOD within them, and conſume their yeares in ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150982:43"/>and vanitie, as though it ſhould neuer be ſaid: <hi>Stand foorth, and giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thy Stewardſhip.</hi> And as there is no kind of life, more commendable in the ſight of GOD and men, then that which doth ſhewe forth in practiſe, the goood graces that God hath beſtowed, to the comfort, encouragement, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of others: ſo is there nothing more to bee diſpraiſed, then to ſuffer Gods gifts to lie hid, and as it were to be buried within vs, and to wrap vp that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in a napkin, as the Goſpell ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, which was put into our hands to vſe, to great commoditie &amp; aduantage. The more our time is idly ſpent, the more we haue to anſwere: and the more that we haue ſpent the time in good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, the leſſe we haue to feare. Nay when the latter day of iudgement ſhall come, happy ſhall they be, of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or calling ſoeuer; happy ſhall that ſeruant be, that is founde to bee ſo painefull. For vnto him it ſhall bee giuen, and from him that had a a talent and vſed it not well, it ſhalbe taken. And this ſhall be their glory and crowne of reioycing, when it ſhalbe ſaid
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150982:44"/>in the preſence of all the people of the world, then aſſembled; <hi>It is wel done good ſeruant and faithfull, thou haſt bene faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in a little, I will make thee ruler ouer much, enter in, into thy maiſters ioy. It is wel done good ſeruant and faithfull.</hi> As I would the contrary ſentence might fear them, that are vnmindful and careleſſe, to ſpend the time wel, which ſhalbe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced then, and at that day againſt them. <hi>Cast that vnprofitable ſeruant into vtter darkeneſſe, there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth; Cast that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruant into vtter darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now moſt fitly to this warning,<note place="margin">Watch.</note> to ſpend our time well, is this counſell gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs to watch. For this iudgement ſhall come as a ſnare vpon the whole earth, and ſhall come at vnawares, to the ydle, wicked, and careleſſe. And better watching there cannot be, then to ſpend the time well. For ſo wee ſhall bee ſure, that whether wee ſleepe or wake, wee bee the Lords: come death, come life, it cannot fall out amiſſe vnto vs. It is ſaid, that the laſt iudgement ſhall come as a theefe in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150982:44"/>the night: and alſo, that the inhabitants of the world, ſhall for the moſt part, if not all of them, be giuen to their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and all licenciouſneſſe, and looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of liuing; as it was in the dayes of <hi>Lot,</hi> when <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorra</hi> were burnt with fire and brimſtone from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> when the windowes of heauen were opened, and when the floud came and ouerwhelmed them all. That ſo iudgement may proceed moſt iuſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that ſhall then be ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſuch filthy and vngodly kinde of liuing. Well are we counfelled by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, &amp; by the Apoſtles, if at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we can ſuffer their counſell to take deepe roote in our hearts. <hi>Now the end of all things</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter, is at hand, be ye therefore ſober and watching in prayer.</hi> Likewiſe alſo his fellow Apoſtle, <hi>Let vs not ſleepe as do other</hi> (where ſleepe is taken for a careleſſe and lewde life) but in all godly and vertuous exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>let vs watch and bee ſober. For God</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>hath not appoynted vs vnto wrath, but to obtaine ſaluation, by the meanes of our Lord Ieſus Christ,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150982:45"/>which dyed for vs: that whether wee wake or ſleepe, we ſhould liue together with him. Take heed therefore</hi> ſaith the Euangeliſt S. Luke. 21.34. <hi>vnto your ſelues, leaſt at any time, your hearts be oppreſſed, with ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting and drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life,</hi> (which matters, the Apoſtle mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by ſleeping) <hi>and leaſt that day come on you at vnawares. Watch and pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, that yee may bee counted worthy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſſe, and that ye may ſtand before the ſonne of man.</hi> And becauſe we know not when this iudgement ſhall be, neither as the <hi>Euangelist, Mar.</hi> 13. ſaith, <hi>Do wee know when the maiſter of the houſe will come, to call his ſeruants</hi> to their reckoning, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will be at <hi>euen, or at midnight; at the cock-crowning, or in the dawning; leaſt if he come ſuddenly,</hi> hee ſhould find vs ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ill occupied: therefore let vs alſo harken to the counſell of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, which doth iumpe and agree with the former. <hi>Take heed</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>watch and pray, for ye know not when the time is,</hi> or ſhall bee, when the trumpet ſhall blowe, to call you to iudgement. <hi>And theſe things which I ſay vnto you, I
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150982:45"/>ſay vnto all: Watch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Not to be curious.</note>Becauſe we know not when this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and laſt iudgement ſhall be, wee are willed to watch, and to be in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe againſt that time: but not to be curious to ſearch Gods ſecrets. <hi>It is not for you,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>to knowe the times and the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> of this waighty matter which God hath kept in his owne knowledge; and this is a miſerie of all miſeries. But the nature of man, as it is wholly deſirous of newes, ſo is it wholly giuen to knowe thoſe things which are hidden, and muſt be hidden: and yet are wee ſo preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, as to creepe and clime into Gods vnſearchable counſell, althogh it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied vs. Wherefore let vs be content, to keepe our ſelues within the bounds of modeſtie, and not to be curious, and deſirous to knowe more then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who are altogether ignorant here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; &amp; much leſſe ſhal we be able to reach vnto it: but the more we deſire to know it, the further off ſhal we be from it.</p>
            <p>Some haue bene ſo bold, as to ſet down the time, and haue fained heauenly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations, for the certaintie and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150982:46"/>of their ſpeeches: yet their vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath beene diſprooued, when the time hath beene expired. How much better ſhall it bee for vs, to lay aſide all ſuch vanitie, which ſtands vpon vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, and giue our ſelues to ſuch a carefull meditation, that wee may not bee vnprepared, when wee ſhall bee called. Curious ſearching can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profit vs, but a wiſe and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreſight and forecaſt, may ſtand vs greatly in ſtead; whereby wee ſhall not bee taken at vnawares, as the vngodly are like to be, who forecaſting no danger, ſhall ſuddenly fall into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>If wee cannot ſufficiently make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto the Iudge,<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> before whoſe iudgement ſeate wee ſhall ſtand, as doubtleſſe wee ſhall not bee able to anſwere one for a thouſand, let vs prepare our hearts by confeſſion of our ſinnes, and by prayer for forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them, and let vs ſay with the Prophet; <hi>Enter not into iudgement with vs O Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no fleſh bee iustified.</hi> O Lord forgiue vs our ſinnes, and let not thy wrathfull diſpleaſure
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150982:46"/>light vpon vs. Who would be vnpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt the time, that ſhall come, and yet it is vncertaine, to teach vs to haue the more care: ſeeing that after death hath arreſted vs, we ſhalbe broght into the court of Gods iudgement, and then no other iſſue, &amp; no other way, but either heauen or hell. And who would not haue a great regard to this matter? For the tryall of this iudgement ſhalbe ſeene in the anguiſh of death, and as it were at the laſt gaſpe, when our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhall bring heauy things to our remembrance; and the diuell by his accuſations ſhall put vs in great feare, and driue vs well-neare to diſpaire. And the nearer wee begin to approach, to the tribunall ſeate of Gods iudgement, the greater ſhall bee our feare, and more grieuous vnto vs, then the bitter pangs of death it ſelfe. Watch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and pray, that thou mayeſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt this time, and againſt this iudgement.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the Lord in mercie,<note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> graunt vs a godly and a peaceable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and that throgh his deſert that dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for vs, it would pleaſe him to mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150982:47"/>and aſſwage all theſe terrorus and feares: and let vs with all ſpeede, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, to the throne of grace, to finde helpe in time of need. Whereas the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked which are careleſſe in their lifetime, at the poynt of death, and at their laſt paſſage out of the world, ſhalbe ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted on euery ſide, by their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience condemning them; and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell accuſing them; and the horrour of euerlaſting torments to come, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelming them; that they ſhall bee driuen to crie out againſt that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that hangeth ouer their heads, and wayteth for them at the doore.</p>
            <p>Such ſhall the day of iudgement bee to vs, as is the laſt day of our life, and looke what the courſe of our life is, when we are called vnto iudgement, (for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our death, immediately commeth iudgement) and ſo ſhall our iudgement be. Neither are we therefore to thinke, that our laſt deedes onely ſhall come to examination: but wee ought to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared euery moment, leaſt death doo take vs vnprouided. For they which in the anguiſh of death, and in the vpſhot of their liues, ſhalbe found vnready, it is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150982:47"/>hardly to be thought, that their reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſhalbe happy.</p>
            <p>And therefore our Sauiour Chriſt hath ſaid: He that perſeuereth,<note place="margin">Perſeuere.</note> and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out well to the end, he ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The which that we may do, let vs be prudent <hi>Noahs,</hi> to build the Arke of a good conſcience, before the floud of iudgement do ouerflowe: prouident <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs,</hi> to lay vp the graine of golineſſe, in the barns of our harts, before the dearth of mercy ſhalbe: like vnto painful ants, to prouide the food of the ſoule, before the winter of iuſtice do approach: trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table patients, to take the preparatiue of repentance, before the pangs of death doo come: wiſe virgines, to haue ready the lampe of faith, and the oyle of vertue, before the Bridgrome Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſhut vp the doores: good ſtewards to prouide for the tabernacle of heauen, before we looſe the office of this life. And let vs not ſtraine curteſie, to ſee who will go firſt: but let vs remember, that euery one is to anſwere for himſelf; and God hath many meſſengers. For either ſickneſſe will come, or age will come: nay death will come ſuddenly
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150982:48"/>and ſpeedily; and after a while we ſhall riſe againe, and the Iudge will come; who will neither be led by fauour or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; nor blinded and ſtopped from proceeding, with bribes and money; nor then will allowe of too late repentance; becauſe then ſhall be the time of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his iuſtice. The day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall come, in the which, pure harts ſhall more preuaile then faire words; and a good conſcience, then great trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And though ſome may thinke, that that day is far off: yet let them be ſure, their laſt time will come on apace, and wee knowe not how ſoone that houre ſhalbe, and when God wil appoint the time. Good it were, and moſt happy for vs, if euery one of vs were ſo affected and ſo prepared, as it is reported of a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father S. <hi>Ierome,</hi> whoſe words were theſe (euen the declaration of his heart: For out of the heart, &amp; out of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance thereof, the mouth ſpeaketh) <hi>Whether I eate</hi> ſath he, <hi>or drinke, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I do, me think I heare this ſound al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in my eares: Ariſe ye dead and come to iudgement: Ariſe ye dead and come to iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:150982:48"/>
            <p>Let vs follow his example, confirmed by the Apoſtles counſell: <hi>Watch and pray withall perſeuerance,</hi> that wee may keepe the garment of innocencie, and labour the worke of God, in the day of this life.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing that day ſhall bee comfortable to the godly, which ſhalbe fearefull to the wicked: let vs endeuour before this iudgement come, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the godly and the righteous: and that our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences may cleare vs ſo wel, that wee may feele within our ſelues, a deſire of this ſecond comming of Chriſt, rather then any tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of it. The which let it not be done by any fained flattery of our ſelues, but in ſinceritie &amp; truth: knowing this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, that whoſoeuer ſhal not be found written in the booke of life, ſhalbe caſt into the lake of fire: where their portion ſhalbe nothing elſe but weeping &amp; gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teeth. That wee may not bee caught in the flaming fire, rendring ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance: but that we may be placed in the heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and reckoned amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſaints of God: that the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may not be a day of eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150982:49"/>vnto vs, but euen the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of our ſaluation and redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the beginning of all ioy &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. While we liue here in this world, let vs be alwayes ready, by ſpending the time well. For as we ſowe, ſo ſhall we reape. As the holy Apoſtle doth put vs in minde. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.8. <hi>Bee not deceiued, God is not mocked. For he that ſoweth to the fleſh,</hi> by practiſing the workes of the fleſh, <hi>ſhall therefore reape corruption:</hi> or rather as if he had ſaid, condemnation. <hi>But he that ſoweth to the ſpirit,</hi> by morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the deeds of the fleſh, by the good motions of Gods ſpirit, ſhall there hence reape euerlaſting life. Which ſentence I pray God print in all our hearts, and ſo graciouſly prepare vs vnto the day of iudgement. Now the very God of peace keepe vs in all well doing, and in all good workes, to do his will, working in vs, that which is pleaſant in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:150982:49"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 36.</bibl>
               <p>The world that then was, periſhed, ouerflowed with water.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Pet. <hi>3.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But the heauens and earth which are now, are kept by the ſame word in ſtore, and reſerued vnto fire, against the day of iudgement, and of the deſtruction of vngodly men. verſ. <hi>9.</hi> The Lord is not ſlack but patient, verſ. <hi>10.</hi> Howbeit the day of the Lord will come as a theefe in the night, in the which, the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noyſe, and the elements ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with the workes therein, ſhall be burnt vp. Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that all theſe things muſt be diſſolued, what manner perſons ought ye to be, in holy conuerſation and godlyneſſe: Looking for, and haſting vnto the comming of the day of God, by the which, the heauens being on fire, ſhalbe diſſolued? But we looke for new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and a new earth, according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe. Wherefore beloued, ſince ye looke for ſuch things, be diligent, that ye may be found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſſe. And ſuppoſe, that the long ſuffering of our Lord, is ſaluation.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:150982:50"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>4.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now the end of all things is at hand. Be ye therefore ſober and watching in prayer.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luk. <hi>21.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take heed to your ſelues, leaſt at any time your hearts be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe, and cares of this life: and leaſt that day come on you at vnawares. For as a ſnare ſhall it come on all them, that dwell on the face of the whole earth. Watch therefore and pray continually, that ye may be counted worthy to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſſe, and that ye may ſtand before the Sonne of man.</p>
               <p>Ariſe ye dead, and come to iudgement.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Treatiſe.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:150982:50"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF the Ioyes of Heauen.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1. Cor. 2.9.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But as it is written.</hi> The things which eye hath not ſeene, neither eare hath heard, neither came into mans heart, are; which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the holy Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> being taken vp into Paradice, heard ſuch words which cannot bee ſpoken, and are not poſſible for man to vtter, as he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of himſelfe, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. How ſhould I take vpon mee, to ſhewe you thoſe Ioyes, which neither eye hath ſcene, nor eare hath heard, nor euer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the heart of man.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:150982:51"/>
            <p>Herein I know mens mindes wil run vpon needleſſe curioſities, which is no part of my dutie to ſatisfie: as alſo to ſhew you mine owne deuices and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, were a thing to ſet forth my owne folly. But ſo far forth as <hi>mans rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> may ſearch, but there we muſt ſtay, for mans reaſon in ſpirituall affaires, is altogether fooliſhneſſe: nay rather ſo far forth as Gods word doth inſtruct vs, we may be deſirous to learne; as alſo to be content, although many things bee hid from vs. Let it therefore be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto vs, if wee may haue but a taſte of thoſe Ioyes, and that it pleaſeth God in a meaſure to graunt vs ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them. <hi>Adam</hi> beeing in the earthly paradice, knewe not all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets and commodities thereof: and how ſhall wee thinke to attaine to the full knowledge of heauenly Paradice? But ſeeing God doth graunt vs the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of theſe matters but after a ſort, he doth it for our good; that ſeeing thoſe ioyes that we can conceiue, are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing excellent, and yet the heauenly ioyes do ſurmount our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits, by many degrees further, we might the more be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150982:51"/>drawne in loue with God himſelfe, who hath ordained ſuch rare, vnſpeakeable, incomprehenſible, and endleſſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, for them that loue him, and liue in his obedience. As alſo conſidering our own great vnworthineſſe, we might with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> breake foorth into the praiſes of God, 14.4.3. and ſay; <hi>Lord what is man that thou haſt ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto him: or the ſonne of man, that thou ſo regardeſt him?</hi> Now as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets doo ſtir vp the peoples mindes, to ſerue and honor God, by ſetting before them the temporal bleſſings of this life; and thereby giuing them an earneſt of greater bleſſings to come: ſo is the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie eſtate of euerlaſting life, deſcribed vnto vs, by ſuch earthly compariſons, as our natural capacitie can conceiue. That we beholding in minde and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thoſe wonderfull Ioyes, which we can conceiue, we may grow into admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe heauenly and incredible excellencies, which are altogether paſt our conceit, and farre beyond our reach and vnderſtanding. For as ſpiritual bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings do far ſurpaſſe corporall bleſſings,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150982:52"/>ſo heauenly ioyes do far exceed al earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory. Yea and theſe ſtately ſecrets of an other life, are ſo much hidden from fleſh and bloud, that all the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the wiſe men of the world, can come nothing neare them. That in this caſe they may truly ſay with the Aſtrologers of King <hi>Nabuchadnezzer, Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>It is a rare thing, and there is no other that can declare them but God himſelfe, whoſe dwelling is not with fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</note>But let vs a little behold what fleſh and bloud hath ſet downe, concerning theſe ioyes of heauen. In the Turkiſh <hi>Alcoran,</hi> that is a booke which they vſe in ſtead of a Bible, which Booke <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> their Prophet left vnto them, as the learned haue ſearched out: thus the ioyes of heauen are ſet downe. Their Prophet promiſeth them, garments of ſilke, of all ſorts of colours; bracelets of gold and amber: parlours and banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſes vpon flouds and riuers; veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of gold and ſiluer, Angels ſeruing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; bringing in gold, milk; in ſiluer, wine; lodgings furniſhed, cuſhens, pillows and downe beds: moſt bewtifull women to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150982:52"/>accompany them: gardens and orchards, with harbors, fountains, ſprings, and all manner of pleaſant fruits: riuers of milk, honey, and ſpiced wine: all manner of ſweet odours, perfumes, &amp; fragrant ſents: and to be ſhort, whatſoeuer the fleſh ſhall deſire to eate. Thus fleſhly people, haue a fleſhly religion, and a fleſhly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice to inhabit: and ſenſual men, haue imagined the ioyes the heauen, according to their ſenſual delights: &amp; yet to them that haue any ſence and reaſon, it canot chuſe, but ſeeme to end all in a fable. Theſe ioyes are ſeene in Princes courts: theſe ioyes are ſeene in the Turkisſh kingdome: but the ioyes of heauen are ſuch, that no eye hath euer ſeene them.</p>
            <p>But to leaue theſe deceiued Turkes, to their falſe and fained ioyes, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what other haue imagined, not much vnlike to this. Which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by way of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon, of a poore mans miſerable eſtate, ſuddenly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, into moſt vnlooked for happineſſe; whereby the ioyes of an other life may appeare, by the miſeries of this life. As if a poore man that were out of his way,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150982:53"/>wandring alone vpon the mountaines, in the midſt of a darke and tempeſtuous night, farre from company, deſtitute of money, beaten with raine, terrified with thunder, ſtiffe with colde, wearied out with labour, almoſt famiſhed with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt, and neare brought vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, with multitude of miſeries; ſhuld vpon the ſuddain, and in the twinckling of an eye,<note place="margin">This cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is ſudden and vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for.</note> be placed in a goodly large, and rich pallace, furniſhed with all kind of cleare lights, warme fire, ſweet ſmels, daintie meates, ſoft beds, pleaſant mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, fine apparell, and honorable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, all prepared for him, and atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, to ſerue him, to honor him, and to annoynt &amp; crown him a king for euer. Behold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> miſeries of this life, &amp; the Ioyes of an other; yet is this but an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and the wit and wiſedome of man, can deuice a great deale more: and yet all are farre inferiour in degree, to thoſe true ioyes, that hereafter ſhall be found. See how the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with their naturall conceits, run all vpon outward comforts, and ſenſuall ioyes, all for the body, and as for the ſoule, that is not once remembred. Now
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150982:53"/>from the deuice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, inuentions, and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of men, all which come nothing neare, to the effect of this matter, let vs now come to the Reuelation of the Scripture, and if any where this bleſſed eſtate be to be found, we ſhall read it in the Booke of the Reuelation. Wherein although many things bee hard and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, and paſſing mans vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, yet is this matter liuely deſcribed after a meaſure, and in a ſort, vnder the name of the citie of God, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it is, that thoſe matters, that neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor euer entred into the heart of man, ſhould ſo much bee opened and reuealed, as there we may read. <hi>Reue.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>Firſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs ſpeak co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the place,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the place where theſe ioyes are to be found, vnder the name of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</note> then concerning the commodities ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to appertaining. The place is heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> the citie of God, the land of the elect: which the Apoſtle deſcribeth after this ſort. And I <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith he, ſawe the holy citie, new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> come downe from God, out of heauen, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a bride, trimmed for her husband. Whereof the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> ſpeaketh in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150982:54"/>the perſon of God, Chap. 65.17. <hi>For loe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I will create new heauens, and a new earth, and the former ſhall not be remembred, nor come into minde. But bee you glad and reioyce for euer, in the things that I ſhall create. For I, behold, I will create</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>as a reioycing, and her people as a ioy. And I will reioyce in</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>and ioy in my people, and the voyce of weeping ſhall be no more heard in her, nor the voyce of crying.</hi> Likewiſe in the Epiſtle to the Heb. 12.22. we may behold the bleſſed eſtate of thoſe that ſhall enioy the life to come. <hi>Ye are come to the mount</hi> Sion, <hi>and to the Citie of the liuing God, the celeſtiall</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>and to the company of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Angels: and to the congregation of the firſt borne, which are written in heauen, and to God the Iudge of all, and to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of iuſt and perfect men, and to Ieſus the mediator of the new testament.</hi> And how this heauenly Citie, and new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is deſcribed, we may read it notably ſet downe in the <hi>Reue.</hi> 21. Where by diuers earthly ſimilitudes, the glory thereof is ſhadowed: ſetting foorth the ſame by thoſe things, which make earthly Cities
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150982:54"/>famous and admirable: as the compaſſe and height of the walles, and ſtately building: the gorgious furniture there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Iewels, and precious ſtones, pleaſant riuers, and the tree of life in the midſt thereof: no night in the Citie. But let vs behold the order and frame of this citie, as we may read in the aforeſaid 21. chap. of the Reuelation, whither ſtill I referre you. The matter declared is as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, beginning at the 12. verſe of the Chapter. <hi>This Citie</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>had a great wall, and a high, and had twelue gates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Church diſperced through the wordld. Therefore the gates, Eaſt, Weſt, North, South.</note> 
               <hi>and at the gates twelue Angels, and the names written, which are the twelue Tribes of the children of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>On the East part, there were three gates: and on the North ſide, three gates: and on the South ſide, three gates: and on the Weſt ſide, three gates. And the wall of the Citie had twelue foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in them, the names of the lambes,</hi> 12. <hi>Apoſtles. And the citie lay foure ſquare, and the length is as large as the bredth of it: and the length and the breadth and the height of it, are equall. And the building of the wall of it, was of Iaſper: and the foundations of the wall of the Citie, were garniſhed with all maner of precious ſtones.</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:150982:55"/>And the twelue gates were 12. pearles, and euery gate is of one pearle, and the ſtreete of the citie is pure gold, as ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning glaſſe. The names of the precious ſtones are further there recited.</p>
            <p>You ſee in theſe words, how glorious this citie of God is: the walles of Iaſper: the foundations, of precious ſtones: the gates of Pearles: the pauement of pure gold. And if the walles, ſtreetes, and gates bee ſuch, how much more ioyfull, comfortable, and incredible, are thoſe things within the citie? for wee muſt perſwade our ſelues, that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hidden treaſures, and matters of farre more account. Many things ſpoken of the outward place, but thoſe things which are within are vnſearchable. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that we read, <hi>Reue.</hi> 2.17. <hi>To him that ouercommeth,</hi> will I giue to eate of the Manna that is hid, and will giue him a white ſtone, and in the ſtone, a new name written: which no man knoweth, ſauing he that receiueth it. So ſecret and hidden are the things within the citie.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> is alſo called a kingdome, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.29. <hi>Therefore</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150982:55"/>to you a kingdome, as my father hath appointed vnto me, that ye may eate and drinke at my table, in my kingdome, and ſit on ſeates, and iudge the</hi> 12. <hi>Tribes of</hi> Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el. And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the godly in all wants, diſtreſſes, and neceſſities in this world, Chriſt ſaith vnto them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.31. <hi>Feare not litle flocke, for it is your fathers pleaſure to giue you the kingdome, and what greater preferment can they looke for?</hi> Yea, which is more, that which but one can haue in a Realme, here euery one ſhall be as a king. Elſe how ſhould it be true, which wee read, <hi>Reue.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Behold, I come ſhortly, hold that which thou hast, that no man take thy crowne.</hi> And that which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of himſelf, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. <hi>I haue fought a good fight, and haue finiſhed my courſe. For henceforth is laid vp for me, the crowne of righteouſneſſe. And the</hi> 24. <hi>Elders caſt down their crowns before the throne of God. Reue.</hi> 4.10. Earthly Princes want no worldly ioyes: and they that weare crowns in heauen, ſhall far more abound in all happineſſe. Thoſe ioies which are higheſt on earth, are of leaſt account in heauen, for all ſhall be crowned. According to the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150982:56"/>ſpeech of the Apoſtle. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is laid vp for me the crowne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous iudge ſhall giue, not to mee onely, but vnto all them alſo that loue his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The place of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where God would be worſhipped, which was in king <hi>Salomons</hi> time, is now there, which we do call the holy land, which in times paſt, was ſo famous, that all nations had recourſe thither. And becauſe of Gods worſhip and ſeruice, and his manifold gracious bleſſings, powred vpon that place, therefore is the kingdome of heauen compared to this, and called the new <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe alſo <hi>Canaan,</hi> that plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full land, which flowed with milke and honey, which was the land that was promiſed to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is compared to this heauenly habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But as many dyed ſhort of it, and neuer entred into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſome for murmuring, ſome for whoredome, ſome for idolatrie, ſome for one offence, ſome for an other: So although wee heare of the ioyes of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150982:56"/>heauen, and of this new Cittie, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would enter therein, yet for their manifold offences in this time of our life, in this time of our triall, many are debarred from thence, and fewe there are, that are made the citizens of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Thus much for the place: now for the commodities.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ioyes of the ſoule.</note>The commodities which belong to this heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> are firſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſoule, beeing the principall part of man. Secondarily, as touching the body: for the body beeing ioyned vnto the ſoule, ſhalbe partaker of this ineſtimable happineſſe: that both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and in ſoule, the whole man may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his full perfection. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is the chiefeſt delight of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minde, to ſerue GOD, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the Church, and in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in this celeſtiall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> there ſhall bee no Temple, no Church. <hi>And I ſawe no Temple therein.</hi> How then? why the preſence of GOD himſelfe, ſhall bee vnto them in ſtead of a Temple and Church. <hi>For the Lord God Almightie, &amp; the lambe, are the Temple of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:150982:57"/>
            <p>Thus in the preſence of God ſhalbe all happineſſe, and at his right hand there are pleaſures for euermore. And as it is ſaid, that the 24. Elders fel down before him, that fate on the throne, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him that liueth for euermore, and caſt their crowns before the throne, ſo ſhall the Saints in heauen, continually ſing forth Gods praiſes, <hi>Reue.</hi> 4.10. and 14.1. The hundred fortie and foure thouſand, which had the name of God in their foreheads, did ſing a new ſong before the throne, and no man could learne that ſong, but the hundred fortie and foure thouſand, which were redeemed from the earth. <hi>Reue.</hi> 7. And there were that were cloathed in long white garments, hauing palmes in theyr hands, which cryed with a loud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> voyce, ſaying: <hi>Saluation be aſcribed to him, that fitteth vpon the ſeate of our God.</hi> And all the Angels ſtood in the compaſſe of the ſeate, which fell before the ſeate on their faces, and worſhipped God, ſaying <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Bleſſing, and glory, and wiſedome, and thankes, and honour, and power, and might, be vnto our God for euermore.</hi> Now ſhall the minde, heart, thought, and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150982:57"/>of thoſe that are thus bleſſed, bee filled with all aboundance of ſpirituall comfort. For now wee ſee as it were, through a glaſſe, but then ſhall wee ſee face to face, <hi>Reue.</hi> 22.4 Then ſhall all errour and darkneſſe of ignorance, bee vtterly taken away: then ſhall wee not deſire as now we doo in this life, to ſee God, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>My ſoule thirſteth after thee. Like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hart deſireth the water brookes, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> my ſoule after thee O God. My ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſt for God, yea euen for the liuing God: when ſhall I come to appeare before the preſence of God?</hi> At that time ſhall all our deſires be fully ſatisfied. And that which was denied the Prophet <hi>Moſes,</hi> to ſee the glory of God in this life, <hi>Exo.</hi> 33.20. ſhall then be graunted to euery one, that there ſhalbe placed.</p>
            <p>The griefe of minde, and ſorrowe of heart, ſhall then be vtterly remoued: no weeping, no mourning, no lamentation to be heard, throghout that holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. <hi>Behold</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> in the perſon of God, Chap. 65.13. <hi>My ſeruants ſhall reioyce, and ſing for ioy of heart: I will ioy in my people, and the voyce
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150982:58"/>of weeping ſhall be no more heard, nor the voyce of crying. Reue.</hi> 21.4. <hi>For God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhalbe no ſorrowe, nor any more paine, for the firſt things are paſt:</hi> that is, thoſe things which wee ſuffred in this life, ſhall not moleſt any more. Then ſhall ſorrow be neuer felt: complaint ſhall neuer be heard: matter of ſadneſſe ſhall neuer be ſeene: neither ſhall euill ſucceſſe at any time be feared. No cauſe of feare, no cauſe of griefe, for that they ſhal poſſeſſe thee O Lord, which art the perfection of their felicitie. In him ſhall wee finde all knowledge, all wiſedome, all bewtie, all riches, all no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, all goodneſſe, all delight, and whaſoeuer beſides, eyther deſerueth loue and admiration, or worketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and contentation. All the powers of the minde, ſhall be filled with the ſight and preſence, and fruition of GOD: all the ſences of our body ſhall bee ſatisfied. GOD ſhall bee the vniuerſall felicitie of all his Saints, containing in himſelfe all particular fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities, without ende, number, or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150982:58"/>He ſhalbe a glaſſe to our eyes, muſicke to our eares, hony to our mouthes, moſt ſweete and pleaſant balme to our ſmell: hee ſhall be light to our vnderſtanding, contentation to our will, continuation of eternitie to our memory. In him ſhall we enioy al the varietie of times, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light vs here, and all the pleaſures and ioyes that content vs here. Finally, the ſoule ſhall bee reſtored to the Image of of God, in full meaſure: and be throgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorned, with all righteouſnes &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, all heauenly and ſpiritual gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ioyes of the body.</note>The commodities and priuiledges of the body alſo, thus vnited to the ſoule, ſhall bee many. And firſt to begin with that which I finde ſet downe in the Text. <hi>And the citie hath no need of the Sun or the Moone to ſhine in it: that is, there ſhalbe ſeene no earthly wants.</hi> For what a great temporall bleſſing, is the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the Sunne, moſt comfortable to man and beaſt, which bringeth forth the fruites of the earth, for mans foode, and without the which, al things ſeeme to be ſad &amp; lowring. But the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we not need this benefite, for the preſence of God
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150982:59"/>ſhall be more comfortable, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God ſhall ſupply the want of Sun and Moone.</p>
            <p>All things then ſhall bee miniſtred vnto vs ſo aboundantly, that wee ſhall not ſo much as once think of any want, whether it be foode, or cloathing, or any comfort of this life whatſoeuer. As the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> doth worthily expreſſe it, Chap. 49.10. <hi>They ſhall not be hungry, neither ſhall they be thirſty, neither ſhal the heate ſmite them, nor the Sun. For he that hath compaſſion on them, ſhall lead them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the ſprings of waters.</hi> Here the body hath need of reſt, but there ſhalbe no night, neither ſhall there be any need of reſt: heere for feare of theeues and enemies, our houſes and the gates of our cities are ſhut, but there the gates ſhall not be ſhut, but alwayes open, becauſe there ſhalbe no feare of enemies, no feare of future hurts and dangers. They that are oppreſſed here, had need of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, of helpe, and comfort, and hardly it is to be had in this world. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. <hi>But there ſhall violence no more be heard of. Eſay.</hi> 60.18. <hi>There ſhall eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ones cauſe be heard, and euery wrong
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150982:59"/>ſhall be righted. For there ſhall be no curſe;</hi> for not onely the courſe of ſin ſhall bee cut off, but all ocaſions of ſinne ſhall far be remoued from vs, and we ſhall bee throughly reconciled vnto our God, and we ſhall enioy perfect peace. As no griefe of minde, ſo no diſeaſe of body ſhall moleſt vs, neither ſhall there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vſe or need of Phiſicke. All infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities ſhall be turned into perfections, and all deformitie ſhall haue an end. That which is now the mighty conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of mankinde, that is death, ſhall then be trode vnder foote: for death ſhalbe ſwallowed vp into victory, that with comfort we may ſay: O death where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victory? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And that which our firſt parents could not taſte of, nor ſo much as touch, that is of the tree of life, (for though they taſted of the tree of knowledge of good and euill, yet they were ſoone caſt out of Paradice, leaſt they ſhould put forth their hand, and take of the tree of life alſo, and eate and liue for euer, <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.22.) in this <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> euen in the midſt of the ſtreete of it, ſhalbe the tree of life, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150982:60"/>paſſage vnto it, <hi>Reue.</hi> 22.2. For this corruptible, ſhall put on incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this mortal, ſhall put on immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. Thus ſhall there be mirth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſadneſſe, health without ſickneſſe, ſtrength without weakeneſſe, life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out labour, light without darkneſſe, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie without abatement, al goodneſſe without any euill. Where youth flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, that neuer waxeth olde: life that knoweth no end, beautie that neuer fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, loue that neuer cooleth, health that neuer diminiſheth, ioy that neuer ceaſeth: there ſhall be pleaſure without paine, and all happineſſe without any change, and life without the reach and gunſhot of death. The godly in this life, are as wares, then ſhall they come to their own poſſeſſion: now they are in the skirmiſh, then ſhal they be crowned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors: now they are in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtuous ſea, then ſhal they be in the quiet hauen: now in the heat of the day, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal they be in the reſt of the euening. Now in place they are abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, thogh in affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they be preſent with him: then ſhal they follow him, whither ſoeuer he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: now they ſuffer trouble with Chriſt,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150982:60"/>though their life be hid in Chriſt: but when Chriſt ſhal appeare, they alſo ſhal appeare with him in glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. and then alſo ſhal they receiue an incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible crowne of glory. According to that warrant which was pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by a voice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen. <hi>Re.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Write, Bleſſed are the dead, which hereafter die in the Lord. Euen ſo ſaith the ſpirit, for they reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, &amp; their works follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And what ioy wil thy ſoule receiue at that day, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhalbe preſented before ſo honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and infirnite a multitude, before the ſeat and maieſtie of the bleſſed Trinitie, with recital &amp; declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all thy good works &amp; trauels, ſuffred for the loue and ſeruice of God, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there ſhall be laide down in that honorable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtory, all thy vertuous deeds, all the laborys y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt taken in thy calling, all thy almes, all thy praiers, all thy faſting, all thy innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of life, all thy patience in iniuries all thy conſtancie in aduerſities? And for their further comfort, and in a maner, woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful aſtoniſhment: as the wicked ſhal be vexed with horrible fear, when they ſhal ſee the righteous ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in great blod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; they ſhal curſe their fooliſhnes &amp;
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150982:61"/>madneſſe, for tormenting ſuch vniuſtly, whom they thought nothing worthy of honour, and yet now ſee them among the Saints of God. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5. So ſhall the righteous in their place, go forth and looke vpon the carkaſſes of the men, that haue tranſgreſſed Gods will and holy lawe, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 66.24. And looking backe vpon the daungers which they haue paſſed, and wherein other men are yet in hazard, their ioy ſhall ſo much the more be encreaſed. For they ſhall euidently ſee, how infinite times they were to periſh in this their mortall life, if God had not held his ſpeciall hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them. They ſhall ſee and behold the daungers wherein other men are plunged, and the death and damnation whereinto many of their friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance haue fallen: the eternall paines of hell incurred, by many that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to laugh and be merry with them in the world: when as they ſhall ſhine as ſtars, which haue conuerted many vnto God. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. As contrariwiſe, they that by their euill example, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold offences, haue bene the cauſe of the downfall of many, ſhall ſuffer intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150982:61"/>griefe.</p>
            <p>In earth, no ioy, pleaſure, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, ſo ſurpaſſing, ſo ſtrange, &amp; ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, but will breed a ſacietie, and we ſhall after a while waxe aweary thereof, either deſiring greater, or elſe longing after varietie; as mans nature is giuen to nothing ſo much, as to newneſſe and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie: but behold, the ioyes of this new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſhall be ſo diuers, ſo ſtraunge, and ſo incredible, that we ſhal neuer be ſatisfied therewith. Which in the <hi>Reue.</hi> 21.2. is expreſſed in theſe words: that the tree of life bare 12. maner of fruites, and gaue fruite euery moneth. <hi>Twelue manner of fruites:</hi> there is the diuerſities of their ioyes. <hi>Giuing fruit euery moneth:</hi> there is the continual change. Stil plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy minde with varietie, and rauiſhing thy ſences with infinite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
            <p>And this may make vs more eager after thoſe ioyes, becauſe we ſhall not be long without them. For the time of this life is but ſhort: and the time of this thy tryall in this world, is but in a manner a moment. If our time here ſhould be a thouſand yeares, what is it to one day in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150982:62"/>the world, which hath no night: which be it, that it hath a ſun-riſing, yet ſhall it neuer haue a ſun-ſetting: an entrance and beginning there is into theſe ioyes, but the termes and date thereof cannot be tolde. And as the torments of hell, whereof I haue heretofore ſpoken, are endleſſe, ſo are the ioyes of heauen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all time: as they are remedileſſe, for out of hell there is no redemption, ſo are theſe ioyes without all change &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration: as they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortleſſe, ſo theſe exceed in al maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts, al without reach, without nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, without meaſure.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I ſhewed you the ioyes of the kingdome of heauen, and yet haue I not ſhewed them: for neither can I vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, nor yet can you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue them. But that which I haue already ſpoken is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, though not for the worthines of the cauſe: or for the ſatisfying of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit deſires: yet for edifying, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, and inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if I ſhould lead you alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with my owne deuices &amp; imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, it were but a matter to delude you: againe neither be you deſirous to knowe more then is fit and conuenient. For when we haue ſpoken all, or the learnedſt in the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150982:62"/>world expreſſed al, yet al muſt fal ſhort of this marke, to vtter the truth of thoſe ioyes. For if no eye hath euer ſeen them, not hart of man can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue them, how is it poſſible, I ſay not for me to declare them, but for any tongue to vtter them? But that which we doo know, let vs ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to our good, &amp; to our neceſſary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leauing off to ſearch, where god wil giue no vnderſtanding. Hidden they are and vnknowne, that wee might the more earneſtly deſire them. For knowne things growe out of loue. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe ioyes already recited, may be ſufficient to eſtabliſh vs, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme vs, that there bee not in any of vs an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful heart, to depart way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. And who wold depriue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of thoſe ioyes, if they were no other, but ſuch as euen our owne minds might imagine, or our own hearts conceiue. In this caſe let vs be content, there to make a ſtop, where Gods word hath ſet a full poynt. And bleſſed be God, who to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs in the way of godlineſſe, hath graunted vs thus to behold theſe incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ioyes, thogh it be but in a ſhadow, and as it were vnder a vaile.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:150982:63"/>
            <p>Howbeit to ſhew you all theſe ioyes,<note place="margin">Application</note> and not to apply them, ſeemeth altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without vſe, and without life. The profitable inſtructions therefore that herehence may ariſe, are more then I can vtter: yet giue mee leaue to recite ſome. And thinke not hardly, though I ſtay you a litle longer. For to heare the diſcourſe of thoſe things which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the kingdome of heauen, I my ſelfe which haue ſearched more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, ſhould in this reſpect forſake my dyet, and forget to heare how the Clocke goes, or the day paſſes. Suppoſe we are now buſie in the field at harueſt, vnmindfull to come euen to our owne houſes, and ſurely this is a farre better harueſt, and a better graine and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, then we can gather in. When it pleaſed God I ſhuld deuiſe this for your good, it was with comfort: and now I vtter it, it is with comfort: and therefore I doubt not, but that you that heare it, heare it alſo with comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To growe out of loue with the world.</note> The firſt inſtruction for our vſe, may be this, to learne to growe out of loue with this preſent world, and with the tranſitory pleaſures and profites of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150982:63"/>ſame: that ſo we may prepare our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to our long home, and to our wiſhed home, and to thoſe houſes and heauenly habitations, whoſe leaſes ſhall neuer be expired: to our heauenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and to his newe and moſt bewtifull <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Howbeit for the moſt part, wee are ſo doted and bewitched with the gliſtring ioyes of this preſent fading world, that no exhortation or perſwaſion ſhal light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preuaile, to withdrawe our mindes from thence. Which thing may liuely be ſet forth to your viewe, by reciting of a Parable of the cuſtome of a certaine Common-wealth, people, and Nation, which were woont to chuſe their king from among the pooreſt ſort of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to aduance him to great honour, wealth, and pleaſures for a time. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a while, when they were aweary of him, their faſhion was to riſe againſt him, and to deſpoyle him of all his felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: yea the very cloathes off his backe, and ſo to baniſh him naked into an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of a far countrey, where bringing nothing with him, hee ſhould liue in great miſerie, and be put to great ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for euer. Which practiſe, one King
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150982:64"/>at a certaine time conſidering by good aduice, (for all the other, though they knew that faſhion, yet through negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and pleaſures of their preſent fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, cared not for it) tooke reſolute order with himſelfe, how to preuent this miſery. Which was by this meanes; he ſaued euery day great ſums of mony from his ſuperfluities and idle expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and ſo ſecretly made ouer before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, a great treaſure into that Iland, whereinto he was in danger daily to bee ſent. And when the time came, that indeede they depoſed him from his kingdome, and turned him away naked, as they had done the other before: he went to that Iland with ioy and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, where his treaſure lay, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued there with exceeding great try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and placed preſently in greater glory then euer he was before.</p>
            <p>This citie, or common-wealth, is this preſent world, which aduanceth to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie poore men; that is, ſuch as come naked into this life, and vpon the ſudden when they looke beſt for it, doth it pull them downe againe, and turneth them naked into their graues, and ſo ſendeth
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150982:64"/>them into an other world, where brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging no treaſure with them, they are like to finde litle fauor, and rather eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall miſerie. The wiſe King that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth this calamity, is euery one which in this life, according to the counſell of Chriſt, dooth ſeeke to lay vp trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heauen, againſt the day of theyr death, when they muſt bee baniſhed hence naked, as all the Princes of that Citie were. At which time, if their good deedes doo followe them, as God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, then ſhall they be happy men, and placed in much more glory, then euer this world was able to giue them. But if they come without Oyle in theyr Lampes, then is there nothing for them to exſpect but this, I knowe you not.</p>
            <p>This ſum of mony, is not ſo much our good deeds, as the forgiuenes of our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold offences, the ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> godly &amp; religious care of the life to come. That which we are ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in loue withall, the Apoſtle giues vs counſel to the quite contrary. Loue not the world, neither the things that are in the world, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2, he addeth the reaſon:
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150982:65"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:150982:65"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:150982:66"/>becauſe the world paſſeth away. But he that fulfilleth the will of God, abideth for euer. Heauen is not in this life, and we muſt looke to bee weaned from this world, if euer we wil looke to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>The ioyes of heauen, and the deſires of the world are quite contrary: for they are too heauy a burthen, and doo hinder vs from mounting vp ſo high. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for the moſt part, wee may be reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled vnto the Graſhopper, which is borne and bred, liueth and dyeth in the ſame ground.</p>
            <p>The Graſhopper hath wings and hoppeth vp a litle, but preſently falleth downe againe. So many of vs haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten good motions vnto godlineſſe, and the life to come: and againe all is gone in a moment, and we returne to our olde affections in this world, as though all our portion were onely in this life.</p>
            <p>Thoſe foules that feede groſly, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer flye high: and they which feed their hearts with things belowe, cannot haue their affections in heauen. The ioyes of heauen being ſo rare and excellent, and ſo ſurpaſſing woonderfull, that they
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150982:66"/>might remoue theſe heauy, lumpiſh, and grouelling deſires of this world. The careleſſe, earthly, and worldly minde, hath no ſight, nor ſence, nor feeling of theſe ioyes. But as the oxe is fatted in the paſture, and the byrd ſingeth ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and feedeth without feare: and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly the one is driuen to the ſlaughter, and the other is taken in the ſnare: So they that are giuen to the world, are lulled a ſleep in ſecuritie, vntil the time that death ſtriketh with his dart, and endleſſe deſtruction ouerwhelmeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But where is that man or woman, which can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I deſire to bee diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt which is beſt of all? Phil.</hi> 1. For they that ſay ſuch things, declare plainely, that they ſeeke a countrey, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.14. Deſiring a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter counttey then is to be found in this world; that is, a heauenly: and for them hath God prepared a Citie. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.14. For here we haue no continuing Citie, no continuing habitation: let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeke a better habitation to come, which is of longer continuance, and free from all miſeries.</p>
            <p>The next fruite is, that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150982:67"/>of theſe ioyes,<note place="margin">Theſe ioyes teach vs patience.</note> teacheth vs pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in affictions, in troubles and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtreſſes. For how troubleſome ſoeuer this life is here, yet there ſhal al troubles, miſeries and wrongs, be aboundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced. And the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth truly. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. The afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent time, are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the glory, which ſhall bee ſhewed vnto vs. In the 126. <hi>Pſal.</hi> They that ſowe in teares ſaith the Prophet, ſhall reape in ioy. And hee that now goeth on his way wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and beareth foorth good ſeed, ſhall doubtleſſe come againe with ioy, and bring his ſheaues with him. <hi>Woe bee to you</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that now laugh, for you ſhall waile and weepe. Luke.</hi> 6.25. And therefore happy ſhall they bee in an other worlde, who haue in good cauſes ſuffered wrongs, committing themſelues vnto God.</p>
            <p>This time of heauenly ioyes,<note place="margin">Heauenly ioyes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a harueſt.</note> is compared vnto harueſt, and what care dooth euery one take to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide good and choiſe ſeede, that theyr harueſt may fall out accordingly.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150982:67"/>Thy ſeede, is thy thoughts, thy words, thy deedes, and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Therefore let mee exhort you as the Apoſtle dooth, <hi>Galla.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Bee not deceiued,</hi> GOD is not moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; for whatſoeuer a man ſoweth, that ſhall hee alſo reape. For hee that ſoweth to his fleſh, ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption: but hee that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit reape life euerlaſting. Looke how wee ſowe, ſo ſhall wee reape: ſuch as our ſeede is, ſuch alſo ſhall bee our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. The date of this our life, is but ſhort, but the remembrance of a life well ledde, ſhall bee comfortable for euer; and this ſhall for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee our endleſſe harueſt: ſtill ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, ſtill encreaſing, and neuer pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing in the aforeſaid 21.<note place="margin">Holineſſe.</note> Chapter, of the Reuelation is, that there ſhall enter into this heauenly <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, no vncleane thing.</hi> And as it is in the Prophecie of <hi>Zechariah,</hi> Chap. 14.21. In that day, there ſhall bee no more the <hi>Canaanite</hi> in the houſe of the Lord of Hoſtes.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:150982:68"/>
            <p>The <hi>Canaanites</hi> were a lewde people, and for the ſame, were driuen out of the land: and if they were not worthy to dwell on earth, much leſſe ſhall they be worthy to be receiued in heauen. <hi>Deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>S. Peter.</hi> 1. <hi>Epist.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Abstaine from fleſhly lusts,</hi> bridle them, keepe them vnder, for they fight againſt the ſoule. <hi>Collo.</hi> 3.1. <hi>If ye be riſen with Christ, ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, where Christ ſitteth at the right hand of God. Set your affections on things which are aboue, and not on things which are on earth: and mortifie your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate affection, and euill concupiſcence.</hi> Remember this peremptory word: <hi>No vncleane thing ſhall enter there. Mat.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God. Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Follow holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without the which, no man can ſee God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And God graunt vs this wedding garment of holyneſſe, that we may goe in with the bridegroome: for we know what befell to him that wanted it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11. Let vs worke our owne ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with feare and trembling: being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to receiue a kingdome, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150982:68"/>bee ſhaken: let vs pray for grace, whereby we may ſo ſerue God, that we may pleaſe him with reuerence &amp; feare. And ſeeing we haue precious promiſes, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. and that more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, then the heauen and the earth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13.18. let vs cleanſe our ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh &amp; ſpirit, and grow vp into ful holineſſe in the fear of God. For as they that thus do his will, ſhal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in through the gates into the Cittie, and their right ſhalbe in the tree of life: So without, ſhalbe dogs, and all vnclean perſons. <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.14. Let not my laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation be forgotten among you. <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the ſtrait gate:</hi> for it is the wide gate and broad way, that leadeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and many there be which goe in thereat. Becauſe the gate is ſtraight and the way narrow, that leadeth vnto life, fewe there be that finde it.</p>
            <p>To adde vnto theſe,<note place="margin">Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, one of the greateſt ioyes.</note> one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ioyes among all, is Gods mercie: whereof wee haue a ſweete taſte in this life. For were it not for that, none of vs all ſhould enter into that place, where thoſse ioyes are to be found. For as our
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150982:69"/>firſt parents, by Gods iuſt anger accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their due deſert, were caſt out of Paradice, and an Angel ſet with a ſword drawne, to keepe the way, that no fleſh ſhould return thither; ſo the onely gate to let vs in again, is Gods mercy. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as the godly and moſt righteous that are, ſtand in great need, ſo let none of vs all, either abuſe Gods mercy, or preſume of his mercy, leaſt we miſſe of the ſame. This mercy, is called the rich mercy of God, for no treaſure is comparable vnto it: and as it paſſeth all vnderſtanding, ſo cannot the deepeſt reach of man, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any part of the depth or height therof: the compaſſe, the largeneſſe, the wideneſſe and breadth of it is ſuch, that it cannot bee meaſured: and therefore may it well be called, as it is indeed, both infinit, and incomprehenſible. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no tongue of man can ſpeake it, let Angels bring the meſſage. As we reade <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Glory be to God in the high hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and peace in earth, and towards men good will.</hi> The Lord of his goodneſſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our ſteppes to this throne of mercy, and cloath vs with the garment of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150982:69"/>And the Lord this day ſet his print and ſeale vpon you.</p>
            <p>Thus I perſwade my ſelf, I haue now wonne ſome, and whom I haue wonne, the Lord in mercy keepe: and ſo I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my ſelfe. For we are all by our owne diſpoſition, like vnto tottering walles, ſtill readie to ſlide, ſtill readie to fall. And therefore I would I might ſay, as it was ſaide to him that ſuffered with Chriſt; This day ſhall ye be in Paradice. And if this day your hatts be throughly conuerted, ſurely this day you are in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice. It was no comfort to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> to remember they wer in Paradice, ſeeing themſelues now caſt out. And if we be once placed in Paradice, then let vs looke to our ſtanding, that we fal not. For as we are mortal, ſo are we mutable: and nothing ſo familiar with vs, as to chaunge. <hi>Deu.</hi> 5.29. Vnconſtant God knowes we are, the Lord make vs ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt. And the remembrance of theſe heauenly ioyes, which wee haue now heard, let that make vs ſtedfaſt euen to the end. </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deo ſoli omnis laus fit &amp; gloria</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi> Et gratia in ſeculum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
